<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breuiat cronicle contaynynge all the kinges from Brute to this daye and manye notable actes gathered oute of diuers cronicles fro[m] Willyam Conquerour vnto the yere of Christ a. M.d.c.lii.</title>
            <title>Chronicles of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1552</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23708212</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23708212</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1832:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breuiat cronicle contaynynge all the kinges from Brute to this daye and manye notable actes gathered oute of diuers cronicles fro[m] Willyam Conquerour vnto the yere of Christ a. M.d.c.lii.</title>
                  <title>Chronicles of England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[215] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Prynted at Canterbury in Saynt Paules parysh by John Mychell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Canterbury] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1552]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]¹⁶ A-C⁸ 2D⁸ 2E⁴ D-L⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  To 1485.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Tudors, 1485-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:1"/>
            <p>A breuiat Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle contaynynge all the Kinges from brute to this daye, and manye notable actes gathered oute of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Cronicles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Conquerour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the yere of chriſt a. M.v.c.lii.</p>
            <p>¶Prynted at Canterbury in Saynt Paules pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſh by Iohn Mychell.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:3"/>
            <head>¶To the righte worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful knight ſyr Antony Anchor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Kinges Iuel houſe, Iohn mychell boke Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wiſheth helthe and proſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He knowledge of hiſtories and cronicles, ryght worſhipfull ſyr Antonye howe pleaſaunte and neceſſarye it is (although part lye I perceue my ſelfe and learned men declare the ſame at large) the common vſe and worldlye practiſe ſheweth euidently, and that it is the recorde of oure forefathers lyfes, without readinge and knowledge wherof we walke in darcknes, and liue like children newe come into the world. But hiſtories and Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles
<pb facs="tcp:26821:4"/> faithfully wrytten ſet before our face, as preſently to loke vpon all ages, all times, all chaunges, all ſtates, and all doinges, euen from the beginninge of the worlde to our owne time, yea, without that we knowe of no world before oure beinge. Much prayſe therfore, and great thankes haue they deſerued which hath truly trauailed in that ſorte of laboure, as dyd that noble clarke Euſebius, and our worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full Contry manne maſter Beade, whoſe worthye doinges I woulde ſome wittie learned man would at this time folowe for an exſample. We had in our Engliſh tonge a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ſhort Cronicle notinge manye thinges worthy of memory, whiche boke I haue by my poore laboure ſumwhat augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, and enlarged with more matter, but oh good Lord nothing to the purpoſe of my good will, if I had as much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:26821:4"/> as I haue deſire of furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and becauſe right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful ſyr Antony I know your good minde, toward the a vauncemente of all honeſt learninge I dedicate this mine endeuor and laboure to youre maſterſhippe moſte hartelie deſiringe your fauourable helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the nexte Printinge of the ſame, by your owne examinacion, or els by the diligence of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by youre maſterſhippe to the ſame aſſigned. Requiring alſo and hartelye prayinge my frences and brothers of the occupacyon of pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſuffer me quietlye to enioye the benefite of theſe mine owne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and to haue the aduantage of myne owne inuencion as I ſhal gladly ſuffer euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enioye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of his, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal brotherlike liue in concorde one by another, this wiſhinge you good life and longe. I byd you fare wel</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Cantorbury. &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:5"/>
            <head>¶To know certayne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .iiii. termes of the yeare concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the lawe begynne and ende.</head>
            <p>¶The terme next after the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of our Lorde, beginneth the xxiiii. day of Ianuary, and endeth the .xii. daye of February.</p>
            <p>¶ Eaſter Terme begynneth the the .xviii. daye after Eaſter, reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge Eaſter daye for one, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the fourth daie after the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of our Lorde.</p>
            <p>¶Trinitie Terme beginneth the morowe after Corpus Chriſti day and endeth the wedneſdaye fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nighte after.</p>
            <p>¶Mighelmas Terme beginneth the ninth day of Octobre, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the .xxviii. day of Nouember.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:5"/>
            <p>¶The Eſcheker is open alwaye viii. dayes before the begynninge of euery Terme.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A true and perfect reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, of the yeres and time, from Adam vnto Chriſt gathered out of the holy ſcripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom Adam vnto Noes floud, are .M.vi.c.lxxxxv</p>
               <p>From Noes flude vnto the departinge of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oute of Chalde are .ccc.lxiii. and .x. daies.</p>
               <p>From the departing out of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, vnto the departinge of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell out of Egipte, are cccc.xxx. yeares.</p>
               <p>From the departing of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell out of Egipt, vnto the fyrſte buyldinge of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:6"/> or elles vnto the fourthe yeare of the raygne of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are .cccc.lxxx. yeares.</p>
               <p>From the fyrſte building of the Temple, vnto the captiuite of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon are .cccc.xix. yeares and vi. moneths</p>
               <p>From the captiuite of Babylon vnto the newe buildinge againe of Ieruſalem are .c.xliii. yeres.</p>
               <p>Frome that time vnto Chriſte are .cccc.lxxxiii. yeare.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_kings">
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:6"/>
            <head>¶ Theſe ben the kynges that haue bene, ſyth Brute came in to this lande fyrſte.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rute came in to thys lande, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the worlde, iiii.M.lxxvii. yeare.</item>
               <item>And he lyued in the lande or he were crowned .lx. yeare.</item>
               <item>And after he was crowned .xx. yere</item>
               <item>Lotrine his ſonne reigned .v. yere</item>
               <item>Madan his ſonne xxx. yere</item>
               <item>Ebranke his ſonne xl. yere.</item>
               <item>Leyly his ſonne ix. yere.</item>
               <item>Bladud his ſonne. xxi. yere</item>
               <item>Guentolin his wyfe xv. yere</item>
               <item>Memps his ſonne xxiiii. yere</item>
               <item>Brute bremenſhull xxx. yere</item>
               <item>Ludebras xiii. yere</item>
               <item>Lyre his ſonne xlviii. yere</item>
               <item>Credell his doughter v. yere</item>
               <item>Conodage her ſiſter ſon. xxxiii. yere</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:7"/>
               <item>Reynolde his ſonne xx. yere</item>
               <item>Gorbodyan his ſonne xv. yere</item>
               <item>Denobaud wan the realme by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and reygned xl. yere</item>
               <item>Bellyn hys ſonne xi. yere</item>
               <item>Cornabatrus his ſon xxv. yere</item>
               <item>Guentolem his ſonne xxv. yere</item>
               <item>Sciſille his ſonne xv. yere</item>
               <item>Kymore his ſonne. xix. yere</item>
               <item>Morwyche his ſonne ix. yere</item>
               <item>Grandobodyan his ſonne xi. yere</item>
               <item>Protegayle his ſonne xvi. yere</item>
               <item>Petitur his brother v. yere</item>
               <item>Eſydur his brother xiiii. yere</item>
               <item>¶And after this Eſydur, reigned xxxiii. kynges, eche after other in peace. The fyrſt king of tho. xxxiii. was Borgodyan, and he reygned xii. yere.</item>
               <item>Morgan i. yere</item>
               <item>Cighnus vi. yere</item>
               <item>Io walam ⚹ viii. yere</item>
               <item>Rohugo xi. yere</item>
               <item>Voghen xiii. yere</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:7"/>
               <item>Catyll xv. yere</item>
               <item>Porrex. ii. yere</item>
               <item>Cheryn xviii. yere</item>
               <item>Coyll ⚹ xii. yere.</item>
               <item>Sulgenis xiii. yere</item>
               <item>Eſdad xx. yere</item>
               <item>Audragie ⚹ ⚹ xvii. yere</item>
               <item>Vrian v. yere</item>
               <item>Eliud ii. yere</item>
               <item>Eldadan xv. yere</item>
               <item>Claten ⚹ xii. yere</item>
               <item>Ouirgunde viii. yere</item>
               <item>Mortan vi. yere</item>
               <item>Bledagh iiii. yere</item>
               <item>Caph ⚹ i. yeare</item>
               <item>Gen ii. yeare</item>
               <item>Seyfell, and kyng Bled xxii. yere</item>
               <item>Gabreth xx. yere</item>
               <item>Archinall xiiii. yere</item>
               <item>Croyll xxx. yere</item>
               <item>Rodyngir ⚹ ⚹ xxxii. yere</item>
               <item>Hectir v. yere</item>
               <item>Harpir vi. yere</item>
               <item>Carpour vii. yere</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:8"/>
               <item>Dygneyll iii. yere</item>
               <item>Samuel xxiiii. yere</item>
               <item>Rede ⚹ ii. yere</item>
               <item>Ely vii. monthes</item>
               <item>Ludde the laſte kynges ſonne of the .xxxiii. reygned xi. yere</item>
               <item>Caſſibalan his brother xxvii. yere</item>
               <item>Androge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Luddes firſt ſon viii. yere</item>
               <item>Kembalyn before the Incarnacion of Cryſte reigned ii. yere</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶The hole ſumme, from the comynge of Brute, tyll the Incarnacion of Chriſt M.C.xxii. yere.</head>
               <item>Grynder and Armog hys .ii. ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. xliiii. yere.</item>
               <item>Koyſe Armog ſonne xli. yere</item>
               <item>Lucy his ſonne reygned an Hethe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man .xi. yere, &amp; a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ii. yere</item>
               <item>And afterwarde was ſo greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in the lande that the realme was without a kynge. l. yere</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:8"/>
               <item>Coyle that made Colcheſter, was king then and reigned xiii. yere</item>
               <item>Conſtantine the Romayne, that wedded Sayncte Elyn Coyles doughter xv. yere</item>
               <item>Conſtantine that was Emperour, his ſonne regned. xx. yere.</item>
               <item>Octauian reygned after that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantyne was gone to Rome, to be crowned Emperour. xv. yere</item>
               <item>Maximian wedded Octauians doughter and reigned. xxviii. yere</item>
               <item>In his time ſaint Albo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſlaine. Conſtantine, coſyn to the kynge of litel Brytayne regned xii. yere</item>
               <item>Conſtantine his ſonne, that was a monke at wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſter reigned v. yere</item>
               <item>Forteger that was Earle of Eſſex reygned xi. yere</item>
               <item>Fortymar his ſonne xiiii. yere</item>
               <item>Engiſt of Saxony in the lande of Germany, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was a Sarazyn: wan the land and reygned. v. yere</item>
               <item>Aurilambros Conſtantines ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:26821:9"/> ſlew Engyſt, and droue the Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zyns away, &amp; reygned viii. yere</item>
               <item>Vter pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brother xvii. yere</item>
               <item>Arther his ſon reigned. xxvi. yere</item>
               <item>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine Arthers coſin. xxiiii. yere</item>
               <item>Guran for Conſtantyne had none heyre, reygned xxx. yere</item>
               <item>Tonagh his coſin xxiiii, yere</item>
               <item>Syryke reygned xxv. yeare</item>
               <item>Saint Ethelbert and Sebert, that were conuerted by ſaint Auſtine &amp; his felowſhip reigned. l. yere</item>
               <item>Elfrede, and Cadwaller, ſaint Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walde, and Cadwalyn reygned, in this realme of Englande one after another. lxxx. yere</item>
               <item>Offa Sainte Oſwaldes brother xlviii. yere.</item>
               <item>Alured the firſt, in his time ſaynte Edmunde of Bury was ſlayne of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and Hubba: the kynges bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of Denmarke. xxx. yere</item>
               <item>Edward the firſt his ſon xxv. yere</item>
               <item>Edmunde his brother xvii. yere</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:9"/>
               <item>Adelſtone xxv. yere</item>
               <item>Eldred his brother. x. yere</item>
               <item>Edwin his third brother iiii. yere</item>
               <item>Edgar his ſonne xvii. yere</item>
               <item>S. Edward the martyr xii. yere</item>
               <item>Swayne that was kinge of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke reygned xv. yere</item>
               <item>Eldred ſ. Edwards brother .ix. yere</item>
               <item>Edmunde Irenſyd, and Knowe Swayne ſonne reigned xx. yere</item>
               <item>Harolde Harefote knowte ſonne xiii. yere.</item>
               <item>Hardeknowt his brother. xvi. yere</item>
               <item>Saynt Edward the confeſſour El<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dredes ſonne reigned xxiii. yere.</item>
               <item>Harolde that was Godwyn ſonne, Earle of well ſex reygned i. yere</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶Here endeth al the kinges that raygned before the Conqueſt.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26821:10"/>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:10"/>
               <head>Wyllyam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queroure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Illiam Duke of Normandy called conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,<note place="margin">Of willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queror duke of norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy.</note> Nephew vnto king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſoure began his dominion ouer this realme of Englande the .xv. daye of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the yeare of oure Lorde .M lxvii. and reygned .xxi. yeares, one moneth with greate cruelnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Englyſhmen chargynge them alwayes wyth greate exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by meanes whereof he cauſed dyuers to flee oute of the lande, he ordayned new lawes at hys owne pleaſure profitable to him ſelf and greuous and hurtful to the people.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond yere of thys ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges
<pb facs="tcp:26821:11"/> reygne the cyty of Exeter and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,<note place="margin">Exiter Rebelled.</note> rebelled which bothe were ſubdued and after greuouſly punyſhed.</p>
               <p>Kynge Wyllyam bylded cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne caſtels within thys realme and put normans to be gouerners in them who greatlye oppreſſed the Englyſhe men.<note place="margin">The eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh men oppreſſed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>About thys time the kyng cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed .ii.<note place="margin">Biſhops &amp; albotes depoſed.</note> Cardynalles to come frome Rome, where by meanes of the kynge they depoſed certayne, Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes, Albottes, and Prioures, Englyſhemen and in theyr place put in Normans.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre aboue yorke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</note>In the .iii. yeare of Wyllyam Conqueroure the Danes inuaded the North countre and won yorke, but ſhortlye after the kynge came and droue awaye the Danes and toke ſuch diſpleaſure wyth the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of that prouynce that he deſtroyed the lande from yorke
<pb facs="tcp:26821:11"/> to Durham, that .ix. yeare after it laye vnlaboured and vntylled.</p>
               <p>About thys tyme was a greate debate betwene Thomas Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of yorke and Langfranke archbyſhop of Canterbury for the Primacy of Englande,<note place="margin">A vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the byſhops for the primacy.</note> but the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Cantorbury optained, and the Byſhop of yorke made to hym an othe of obeyſaunce.</p>
               <p>In the .x.<note place="margin">A conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kynge.</note> yeare of thys kynges raigne Roger Erle of Herford and Rafe Earle of Norfolke conſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red agaynſte kynge Wyllyam he beynge in Normandy, whych were bothe outelawed the realme, and Earle Walrefe, that vttered the conſpiracy was beheaded.</p>
               <p>About the .xv.<note place="margin">A bataile i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy</note> yere of his raigne Robert curteyſe the kynges eldeſt ſone wyth the helpe of Philip the French kinge made warre againſt his father in Normandye where kynge Wyllyam was ſore hurte
<pb facs="tcp:26821:12"/> but afterwarde a peace was made betwene them.</p>
               <p>Thys kynge wyllyam made the newe foreſt in hamſhere and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he caſt downe diuers churches by the ſpace of xxx.<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of new foreſt</note> myles.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe man bare office in engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note>In his time he kept the Englyſh men ſo lowe that few of them bare any offyce of honour in England.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the .xix. yeare of kynge Wyllyams reygne he beynge in Normandy rayſed a great trybute in England and cauſed to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of euery hyde of landes whych contayneeh .xx,<note place="margin">A greate tribute.</note> Acres .vi. s</p>
               <p>Shortly after the kinge made warre into Fraunce where he dyd muche hurte,<note place="margin">The deth of willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queror.</note> but in this heate he toke ſuche a diſeaſe that it coſt him his life, in his ſekenes he made his teſtamente, and gaue to Wyllyam Rufus his ſecond ſonne the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Englande, and to Roberd Courteiſe his eldeſt ſonne the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chye
<pb facs="tcp:26821:12"/> of Normandy, and vnto he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hys thyrde ſonne he gaue hys treaſure, thus he ended his lyfe in the moneth of Iuly and lyeth bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed at Cane in Normandy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Wylliam Rufus</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Illyam Rufus or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam the Reed began his reygne ouer thys realme the .xvii. day of Septembre the yeare of Chriſt .m.lxxxix. Sone after wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyam Rufus had taken vpon him the kyngdome, hys brother Robert Courteiſe came out of Normandy and landed at hampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thentent to haue put out his brother frome the kyngdome but the kynge ſente to him ambaſſadours,<note place="margin">Agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwene willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus &amp; hys brother.</note> ſo at the laſt they were agreed that Wyllyam Rufus ſhould be kynge payinge to his brother yearly .iii.M. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:26821:13"/> &amp; ech of them to be others aire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſte the kinge.</note>In the ſecond yere of thys king dyuers Lordes in England rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt the kynge and aſſayled dyuers townes, but kyng wylliam vanquyſhed the traitours and cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed them out of hys realme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">war with the ſcotes</note>In the .iii. yeare of Wyllyam Rufus the ſcottes warred on eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, wherefore kynge Wyllyam prouided an armye and wente the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where after dyuers conflictes and ſcermyſhes a peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded ſo that Malcolyn kynge of Scottes was ſworne to be trew to kynge Wyllyam.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A greate winde in England</note>In the iiii. yere of wyllyam Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus there was a greate wynde, in London that blew downe v.c. hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and the rofe of Bow churche, and did greate hurte in vyncheſter and other places.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king of wales ſlayne.</note>In this time alſo the Welche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men rebelled, but they were ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:26821:13"/> theyr duke or kinge called Ryſe ſlayne whiche was accompted the laſte kinge of Wales.</p>
               <p>Alſo Malcolin kyng of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes rebelled and came with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into Englande,<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes ſlayne:</note> but the Earle of Northumberlande encountred wyth him, and there kinge Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colyn was ſlaine.</p>
               <p>In the .vi.<note place="margin">a viage to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> yeare of William Ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fus there was prepared throughe chriſtendome a mightye army of thre .c.M. men to winne Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe ſoueraygne capitayne was Godfrey duke of Loraine and his ii, bretheren with many other noble men of Chriſtendome.</p>
               <p>At this time many noble menne<note place="margin">Borowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of money for this vyage</note> laied their landes to morgage to prouide for the forenamed viage a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monge whiche was Roberd Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toyſe Duke of normandy he layed his dukedome to pledge to his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther William kinge of Englande
<pb facs="tcp:26821:14"/> for a C.M. pounde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Greate taxynge.</note>A bought the .viii, yeare of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Rufus bothe Englande and Normandy were greuouſlye taxed, and alſo there was a great morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie amonge menne ſo ſharpe that tillage of the earthe was put of for that yeare whereby enſued greace hunger and ſcarcitie in the yeare folowinge.<note place="margin">Greate morallity</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hall builded.</note>Abought the xi. yeare of the king he builded Weſtminſter halle.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo the chriſten men wan Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after they had beſeged it xxxix.<note place="margin">Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wonne by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men.</note> daies and Godfry the ſoueraine captaine of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men was proclaimed kinge of Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rufus.</note>This kyng William had great pleaſure in hunting inſomuch that he pulled downe many houſes of religion to enlarge the newe eoreſt of Winſore for wilde dere, but a Frenche knyght of his named wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:26821:14"/> Cerel by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaunſynge of hys arowe vpon a braunche when he ſhote at a harte in the ſayde foreſt, ſmot the kynge and wounded hym to deathe, whereof he ſhortlye dyed in the yeare of oure Lorde. M.C. wythoute anye yſſue of his bodye, and he raygned .xii. yeare and .xi. monethes and is buried at weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Henry the firſte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry the brother of Wyllyam Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus and fyrſte of that name (for hys learnynge callyd Beweclarke) and thyrd ſonne to Wylliam Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure was crowned kynge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land the .v. day of Auguſt the yere of our Lord .M.c. and .i.</p>
               <p>This Henry was a noble prince
<pb facs="tcp:26821:15"/> in the fyrſt yeare of his raygne he reformed the meaſure in England whiche of longe time were corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he vſed the lawes of ſaynt Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,<note place="margin">Meſures reſtored.</note> ſone after he was kynge he toke to wyfe Maude the ſyſter of Edgare kynge of Scottes. Thys man fauoured nothynge the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped powre of the byſhop of Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king releſed of his tribut</note>In the .iiii. yeare of this kyng Roberd curtoyſe the kynges bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there came into englande and was well entreated of the kynge and Quene and there the duke releaſed the kynge of his tribute of .iii.M. markes, but it was not longe after by meanes of tale bearers and yll reporters that great variaunce fell betwene the kynge,<note place="margin">Duke Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoner.</note> and the Duke of Normandy hys brother, and ſhortlye thereupon deadlye warre was arrered in thend wherof duke Roberd was taken and kepte in perpetuall pryſon at cardyffe, by
<pb facs="tcp:26821:15"/> his brother, who immediatlye ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the duchye of Normandy and helde it in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>In the .vi.<note place="margin">A rebelio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> england</note> yeare of kynge hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the fyrſt, the Earle of ſhrewyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, and the Earle of Cornewall rebelled againſte kynge henry and after were taken and kepte in pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as longe as they lyued.</p>
               <p>About this tyme alſo the kyng ordayned ſtrayghte lawes agaynſt theues and other that vſed vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meanes, whiche were puniſhed,<note place="margin">Puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours.</note> ſome with death, ſome with loſſe of their eyes, of their ſtones and other membres of man as theyr treſpas requyred.</p>
               <p>By the meanes of Anſelme by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Cantorbury the preeſtes of England were conſtrayned to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go theyr wyues whiche before was lawfull to be maryed.<note place="margin">The pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraned to forgo their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Aboute the .xiii.<note place="margin">An earthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quake.</note> yeare of kynge Henries raygne was a great earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quake
<pb facs="tcp:26821:16"/> at ſhrewſburye and the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Trent was ſo drye that men myght go ouer drye ſhode.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene england &amp; Fraunce.</note>In the .xvii. yeare of king hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries raygne began great varyence betwene Lewes frenche kinge and kynge henry of Englande and at the laſt was fought betwene them a cruell battayle where the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe menne optayned the victory and the frenche king fled, but ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly after a peace was concluded and wylliam the eldeſt ſonne of kynge henry dyd homage to the frenche king for the Duchy of Normandy</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges two ſonnes drowned.</note>In the .xx. yere of Henry the firſt Wyllyam duke of normandye the kinges eldeſt ſonne, and Richarde his brother, and Mary theyr ſiſter, Richard Earle of cheſter with hys wyfe the kynges nece, and other to the nombre of a .c. and .vi. perſons paſſing from Normandy into Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande by ouer ſyghte of the ſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter
<pb facs="tcp:26821:16"/> were drowned and none ſcaped but one man.</p>
               <p>Aboute the .xxvi.<note place="margin">A law or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daned for preeſtes.</note> yeare of thys kynge there was a counſell holden at london wher it was determined that the abominable vices of the preſtes ſhoulde be puniſhed by the kinges offiters.</p>
               <p>In the .xxii.<note place="margin">maude the empreſſe made aire of the Realme.</note> yeare of kyng hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries raigne bycauſe he had none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iſſue male, ordayned that hys doughter Maude which had bene Empreſſe ſhoulde ſuccede him in the kyngdome.</p>
               <p>A boughte the .xxviii.<note place="margin">maude the empreſſe maryed.</note> yeare one Geffery Plantagenet Earle of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geo maried the ſaide Maude and by her had iſſue henry whiche hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after kinge Steuen was kinge of Englande.</p>
               <p>This kinge henry the firſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in Normandy in the .xxv.<note place="margin">The deth of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry the fyrſte.</note> yere of his reigne the ſecond day of De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cember in the yere of Chriſte a .M
<pb facs="tcp:26821:17"/> a .c.xxxv. dyed, ſome ſay of a ſurfet, and ſome writers ſaye it was by a fall of a horſe. And his bodye was brought into England and is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Abbey of Reding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of King ſteuen.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Teuen Earle of Boloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, the ſonne of the earle of blois, and Adela wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querours dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Nephew to Henry the firſt, toke on hym the gouernaunce of this realme of England throughe the counſaile of manye Lordes of Englande contrarye to theyr othe made to Maude the Empreſſe, and was crowned king vpon ſaint Ste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens day the yeare of Chriſt .M.c. and xxxv.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Variance i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> england</note>At this time there was greate variance in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for king Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen was thoughte to be kinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtlye
<pb facs="tcp:26821:17"/> for manie of the Lordes of Englande fauoured Maude the Empreſſe, and other fauored Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen who was kinge of the whiche folowed greate warre.</p>
               <p>This kinge ſteuen beſeiged di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers caſtels that belonged to Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and other lordes and toke them by forſe,<note place="margin">Caſtelles beſeged.</note> and fortified them with his owne knightes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, to thentente to withſtand the empreſſe whoſe comminge he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer feared.</p>
               <p>In the ſeconde yeare of kinge Steuen there roſe a greate rumor in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that king Steuen was deade whiche tales roſe much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaunce in England for diuers of the lordes got them to their holdes whiche after might ſcantly be pace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied or quieted.<note place="margin">yll talles doth much hurte.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Shortly after the kinge wente<note place="margin">A viage to nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</note> into Normandye and kepte warre with the Earle of Aniowe the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
<pb facs="tcp:26821:18"/> of Maude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empreſſe which was righte aire to the Crowne of England and when he had quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that prouince he made Euſtace his ſonne duke of normandy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A bataile &amp; the king taken pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoner.</note>In the .vi. yeare of king Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Maude the Empreſſe came in to England by the comforte of the Earle of Gloceſter and the Earle of Cheſter, and made ſtrong warre vpon kinge Stephen in the ende whereof the kinges partie was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come, and him ſelfe taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and was brought to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe who ſente him to Briſtowe to priſon.</p>
               <p>Shortlye after this bataile the kentiſh men and londoners roſe &amp; toke parte with the king,<note place="margin">A bataile at wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> &amp; at a feld foughten at wincheſter they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Empreſſe, and ſhe flede to Glouceſter and Earle Roberte of Gloceſter was taken, but ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after bothe the kynge and earle
<pb facs="tcp:26821:18"/> Roberte were delyuered out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by exchaunge.</p>
               <p>Shortly after the kynge gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a greate power,<note place="margin">To e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>preſſe beſeged.</note> and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe fled vnto Oxforde where the kynge dyd beſege her, but ſhe fled awaye by nyghte, and ſo wente to Walyngford, and ſhortlye after with a ſmalle companye ſhe wente into Normandy to her huſbande Geffery Plantagenet.</p>
               <p>Aboughte the .x.<note place="margin">A childe crucified i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſpyte of Chriſte.</note> yeare of kynge Steuens raygne, the Iues that dwelt in England toke and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied a chylde at Norwytch on Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter day in deriſion of Chryſte and hys relygion.</p>
               <p>In the .xi.<note place="margin">The deth of Gefery Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginet.</note> yeare of kynge Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Geffery Plantagenet Erle of Aniowe and huſbande to Maude the Empreſſe, after he had wonne from kynge Steuen the Duchy of Normandy ended his life, and He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his ſonne ſucced in that dukedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:19"/>
               <p>Henry Duke of Normandy, in the quarell of hys mother Maude the Empreſſe with a great puſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce entred into Englande,<note place="margin">Henri the ſecond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and.</note> and at the fyrſt wan the Caſtell of Malmeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, then the Towre of London, and afterwarde the towne of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngham, with other holdes and Caſtels, betwene hym and kynge Steuen were fought manye Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayles whereby thys realme was ſore troubled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A peace be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene the Empreſſe and kinge Steuen.</note>In the .xviii. yeare of kyng Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen peace was agreed betwene Maude the Empreſſe, her ſonne, &amp; kynge Stephen on thys condicion that Steuen ſhould be kynge du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng hys life, but for al this peace, kynge Steuen toke ſuche thought and care that he died in the .xv.<note place="margin">The deth of king Steuen.</note> day of Octobre nexte folowynge, in the yeare of Chryſte .M.C.liiii. for he was in warre and trouble all the terme of hys lyfe and he was bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:26821:19"/> at Feuerſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>⚹ Henry the ſecond.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry the ſeconde and ſonne to Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery Plantagenet erle of Angeo and maude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empreſſe, was crowned king the .xx. daye of Decembre the yeare of Chryſte .M.c.lv.</p>
               <p>Thys kyng was a noble man,<note place="margin">Henry the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his kingdome</note> and muche fortunate in warres, &amp; greatlye enlarged his kyngdome. But diuers wryters whiche more dyd fauoure the doynges of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becket then the truthe, wryte that in his latter daies he was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunat, but by his great manhod and pollycy the ſyngnory of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was muche augmented with the addicions of Scotlande, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, the yles, Orcades, Britaine.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:20"/> Poytow, Gyon, and other prouince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of fraunce, wherfore it may be euydent to all men that hys good wyl was to reforme in his tyme the clargie, but as then god had not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defacing of caſtels.</note>In the ſeconde yeare of kynge Henry the ſeconde, the kynge caſte downe diuers caſtels whiche were ſet vp in the tyme of kynge Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to defende Maude the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his mother.</p>
               <p>After that he went into the north partes and receyued of the kynge of Scottes,<note place="margin">A voiage into the Northe countre.</note> Cumberland, and Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thumberland, which they ſayd wer geuen to them, by Maude his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſet an order in that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Wales.</note>In the .iii. yeare of kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes reigne he wente with a ſtrong Armye into Wales and quietted that countrey, and after buylded the ſtronge caſtel of Rutland.</p>
               <p>About the .v. yere of this kinges
<pb facs="tcp:26821:20"/> reygne roſe a greate Schiſme at Rome for ſome of the Cardynals choſe one octauian,<note place="margin">A ſchyſme at Rome.</note> and other ſome woulde haue Alexander to be By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, whyche Schiſme continued xx. yeares and muche trouble folowed.</p>
               <p>In the .vii.<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</note> yeare kynge Henry kepte ſuch warre in to Scotlande that he toke kynge Wyllyam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner whiche afterward was dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and the kynge of Scottes dyd fealtie and homage to kynge Henrye.</p>
               <p>In the .x. yeare of thys kynge Thomas Bocket archebyſhop of Cantorbury (whyche ſediciouſlye vnder pretence of defending the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the churche (as he ſayde)<note place="margin">Thomas becket fled the realme</note> ſpake and dyd manye thynges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the kynges prorogatyue royall) dyd flee out of the realme, &amp; went to Rome to complayne vpon the kynge to the Byſhop.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:21"/>
               <p>In the xvii. yeare of kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Thomas Becket by entreaty of the byſhoppe of Rome,<note place="margin">Thomas becket ſlayne.</note> and Lewes the Frenche kynge was reſtored to his Byſhopryke, and not longe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by certeine gentilme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſlain.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">more fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the byſhop of Rome.</note>Kyng Henry in the .xviii. yeare of his reygne ſent Ambaſſedoures to the byſhop of Rome to pourge hym ſelfe of the falſe accuſacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Thomas Becket but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other thinges it was enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the kinge in his penaunce that it ſhoulde be lawfull to all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes as often as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liſt to apeale to the ſea of Rome, and that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde be accompted as king vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as he were confirmed by the Romyſh Biſhop. By thys all men may perceiue that the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome alway deſired to haue princes and kinges readye at their becke, but this Eniuncion was neuer fulfiled of the kynge of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:21"/> Englande.</p>
               <p>In thys yeare alſo kynge Henry went into Ireland and ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dued it,<note place="margin">Irelande wonne.</note> and anexed Irelande to his kyngdome.</p>
               <p>In the .xxii.<note place="margin">The kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges eldeſt ſonne crowned Kyng</note> yeare of kinge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry he cauſed Henry his eldeſt ſonne to be crowned kynge and maryed Margeret the Frenche kynges doughter.</p>
               <p>Shortlye after kynge Henry the ſone at the ſettyng on of the french kynge and the kynge of of ſcottes,<note place="margin">warre be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene the father &amp; the ſonne</note> wyth dyuers other made warre a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſte kynge Henry his father where were betwene them dyuers ſtronge battayls but alwayes the father had the victorye, and at the laſte his ſonne with his alyees wer conſtrayne to bende, and deſyre peace whiche he gentyly graunted and forgaue their treſſpaſſe.<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonner.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In thys warre Wylliam king of Scottes was taken pryſoner
<pb facs="tcp:26821:22"/> and yelded for hys raunſome the cytie of Carlyle, the caſtell of Bam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>broughe, the newe caſtell vpon Tine, and ſwore for euer to be trew to the kinge, and aſwel he to do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage as his ſucceſſours as ofte as they ſhould be requyred.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">many Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</note>About thys tyme were manye Iues in England, which agaynſt the feaſte of Eaſter, dyd vſe to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie yonge chyldren in deſpyte of chriſtian relygion.</p>
               <p>In the .xxviii. yeare, Henry the eldeſt ſonne of Kynge Henrye of England ended his lyfe.<note place="margin">warre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in Fraunce.</note> Shortlye after began the warre in fraunce for kinge Philip of Fraunce deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red homage to be done to hym for the landes of Poytow and other, and for the caſtell of Gyſours.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde.</note>In the .xxxiiii. yeare of kynge Henry the ſeconde Richard Earle of Poytow mayde warre a gaynſt kynge Henry of England hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:22"/> and takynge parte wyth the frenche king wan from hys father many townes &amp; caſtels, for ſorowe wherof ſhortly after kynge Henry ended his lyfe in the yeare of chriſt m.c.lxxxviii, &amp; is beryed at founte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerarde in fraunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Rychard the fyrſte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ichard the firſte, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſonne of kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the ſeconde was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned kynge of Englande the, iii. day of September the yere of Chryſte .M.c.lxxxix. This man for hys valyantneſſe and corage was called Curedde lion.</p>
               <p>In the fyrſt yeare of kyng Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde the Londoners obtayned two offycers to gyde theyr cytie whiche were called baylyffes.<note place="margin">Two bay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liffes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</note> 
                  <note place="margin">The Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſpoiled at london</note>
               </p>
               <p>About this time the Iues bare themſelues very bolde in London
<pb facs="tcp:26821:23"/> in ſo muche that the people roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte them and dyd robbe and kyll many of them without pytie. But by cauſe the offendours were ſo manye they aſcaped wythoute punyſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king of ſcottes did ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age</note>Alſo in this fyrſt yeare Wylly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am king of Scottes came to Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torbury and dyd homage to kynge Rycharde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A prerara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</note>About this time the prynces of Chriſtendom made great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon to recouer Hieruſalem and to ayde the Chryſtyans in Aſia.</p>
               <p>In the thyrd yeare of king Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,<note place="margin">the iſle of cipres con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quered.</note> he with a noble army toke his Iorney toward Hieruſalem &amp; by the way he conquered the yle of Cypres, and afterward he Ioyned wyth the french kynge in Aſia, and conquired Acon, but ſhortlye after there fell great variaunce betwene kynge Richard of Englande, and kynge Philyp of fraunce wherfor
<pb facs="tcp:26821:23"/> kinge Philip returne whome in to Fraunce and inuaded Normandy, &amp; alſo he counſaled Iohn the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to kynge Rychard to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hym the kingdome of England in his bothers abſence.</p>
               <p>Shortly after kynge Rychard of England reſtored to the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the citie of Ioppe,<note place="margin">The citie Ioppe wonne,</note> and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye battayles put the Turkes to muche ſorowe.</p>
               <p>In the .iiii.<note place="margin">The cruel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of the byſhop of Elye.</note> yeare of kyng Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and while he was in Aſſia wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam byſhoppe of Elye, to whome king Richarde had committed the gouernaunce of Englande, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed muche crueltie as in depreuing of byſhoppes and Abbottes, and wolde ryde with a .M. horſes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he greued the place where he ſo iourned. But at the laſt by ſtrength y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes put hym out of the land.<note place="margin">Kynge ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</note>
               </p>
               <p>King Richard exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged Cipers with Guye of Leſingham for the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:24"/> kingdom of Hieruſalem wherfore the kinge of Englande of a longe time after was called king of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">king Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er</note>In the .v. yeare king Richard hearing that king Philip of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce inuaded Normandy: &amp; that Iohn his brother aſpired to his kingdom toke peace with the Turkes for .iii. yeares and with a ſmall company returned whomewarde by Thrace and there was trayterouſlye taken priſoner by the Duke of Auſtrych and brought him to henry the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and he was kept in ſtreight priſon a yeare, and .v. monethes where it is ſaid he ſlew a Lion and toke out his harte.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">king Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>In the .vi. yeare of kinge Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardes raygne he payed his ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome whiche was a .C.M. pounde and was deliuered, and retorned to his countre, and made ſharpe warre vpon the frenche kynge, and
<pb facs="tcp:26821:24"/> Iohn his brother at whiche tyme was fought diuers great batailes to the greate loſſe of both partyes.</p>
               <p>In the .viii.<note place="margin">peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land and Fraunce,</note> yeare of kinge Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardes reygne there was a peace concluded betwene Englande and fraunce for one yeare, and Iohn ſubmitted him ſelfe to his brother.</p>
               <p>In the .x.<note place="margin">Auriculen confecion firſt enue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> yeare of king Richards raygne, Innocent the .iii. Byſhop of Rome, he firſte compelled men to Auriculer confeſſion, and forbad the Sacrament to be miniſtred to the layetie vnder both kyndes.</p>
               <p>Shortlye after the warre was newe arered betwene England and fraunce wherfore kinge Richarde ſailed againe into Normandy and made newe warre vpon the french kynge, in whiche warre they ſpede diuerſly, for ſome time the Frenche kinge wan holdes in Normandy, and ſome time the kinge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande wan in Fraunce. But at the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:25"/> laſt kinge Richard went to beſege a Caſtell called Caſtell Gayllarde and as he rode aboute the Caſtell to auew it one marked him,<note place="margin">The deth of king ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chard the fyrſte.</note> &amp; ſmot him with a Quarrell in the heade whereof anone after he dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute yſſue of his bodye in the yeare of Chriſt .M.cc. and in the .xii. yere of his reigne. And is buried at Fountuerarde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Kinge Iohn.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn brother to the aboue named Richard was crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned king of England the xvii.<note place="margin">ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Iohn co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yned the biſhop of rome of a frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard minde</note> daye of Iuly the yeare aboue wrytten and reigne .xvii. yeares. This kinge contemned the biſhop of Romes aucthoryte, whiche if he had done of conſcience and for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſake, as he ſemed to do for couetouſnes, and of a frowarde minde, vndoubtedlye he had bene
<pb facs="tcp:26821:25"/> worthy hye commendacion. By his cowardnes and ſlothful necligence the ſignorye of Englande greatlye decayed.</p>
               <p>In the firſt yere of kyng Iohns raygne kinge Philyp of Fraunce (in the quarell of Arthur Duke of Brytaine whome ſertaine of the lordes had named kinge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) made war vpon kinge Iohn and inuaded Normandy and toke from him diuers Caſtels and tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but after long Scirmiſhes,<note place="margin">warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwen England &amp; Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of both parties, a peace was a greed which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not longe.<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes did ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yere the king of Scottes came in to Englande and dyd ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and ſware to be trewe leage man to king Iohn of of England.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond yere in yorkeſhire wer ſene v,<note place="margin">A ſharpe wynter.</note> mones at ones in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; the next winter after was a ſharpe winter &amp; hayle felle as byg as hennes Egges.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:26"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Arthur of Bretaine taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner:</note>In the .iii. yere of kinge Iohns raygne kinge Philip of fraunce in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaded Normandy and toke diuers caſtels and townes which he gaue to Arthur Duke of Bretaine. But ſhortly after the ſame Arther with many other noble men were taken priſoners by king Iohn and led in to Englande.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Englande enterdited</note>In the .vi. yeare of this kinge the byſhoppe of Rome demounced kinge Iohn with his whole realme accurſed, becauſe he would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſteuen Laughton to the biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prike of Cantorbury. But he lyttel regarded his curſe nor obeyed hym nothing the rather.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy loſte.</note>In the .vii. yere of kyng Iohns Rayne, kynge Philyp of Fraunce ſubdued to him the countre of Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandye, which was not vnder the dominion of Fraunce in .ccc. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res before.</p>
               <p>Aboute thys tyme the Welche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:26821:26"/> and Iryſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rebelled, whom kynge Iohn conſtrayned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme peace with greate ſommes of money.<note place="margin">The wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che men &amp; Iriſhe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rebelled.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Aboute this time Philip Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Almaine was murdered by the treaſon of the countye Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentyne.<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure murdered</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the .ix,<note place="margin">The firſt mayre of London,</note> yere of kynge Iohns rayne was fyrſte ordayned may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and ſhyriffes in London, and the fyrſte mayers name was Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Fitz Alwyn, and the fyrſte ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes wer Peter Duke, and Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Nele.</p>
               <p>Aboute the .xiii.<note place="margin">ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Iohn reconſiled to the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome.</note> yeare of kinge Iohns rayne Philippe of fraunce made ſharpe warre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> England at the ſettynge on the Byſhop of Rome. Inſomuch that kyng Iohn was fayne to ſubmite him ſelfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh biſhop, who was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that aſwell he as his ayres ſhould hold the crowne of the byſhoppe of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:27"/> Rome, and ſhould paye yearelye a M. Marke of ſyluer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iewes the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſonne entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note>In the .xvi. yeare of king Iohn great ſtrife and varyaunce happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in England betwene the kyng and his Lordes, and commons of his realme. Inſomuche that the kynge ſente into flaunders for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure and the nobles ſent for Lew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es the ſonne of kinge Phylyppe of fraunce, and him ſaluted as kinge, &amp; mayntayned him in war againſt kynge Iohn to the great hurte of this realme of Englande. Duryng the tyme of this warre King Iohn ended hys lyfe and died of the flixe at Newewarke vpon Trent the .xix daye of Octobre the yere of Chryſt M.cc.xvi.<note place="margin">The deth of king Iohn.</note> But ſome Authors wryte that a Monke poyſoned him at Swyneſted, and is buryed at Worceſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Henry the thirde.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:27"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry the thyrd of of that name, and eldeſt ſonne to ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Iohn by the ayde of certayne lordes of Englande was crowned kynge at .ix. yeares of his age whiche kinge wyth his aydes kepte ſharpe warre whiche Lewes the frenche kynges ſonne, who by comnaunte of certayne Lordes of England claymed the crowne,<note place="margin">Iewes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> but after certagne Skyrmyſhes and battayles a peace was concluded, ſo that Lewes ſhoulde departe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce and for his trauayle he had a m. Markes and ſo departed</p>
               <p>In the fyrſt yeare of king hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes raygne were ordayned many lawes in Englande to the greate commoditie of his ſubiectes.<note place="margin">Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carta co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</note> And the greate charter called Magna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carta was confirmed, and diuerſe articles added thereto.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:28"/>
               <p>In the forthe yeare Alexander kynge of Scottes maried Ioan the ſyſter of kynge Henry of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes maried.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo there was a Proclamacion made throughe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute Englande to auoyde ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.<note place="margin">Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers put out of the realme.</note> Becauſe one Foukes de brent held the caſtell of Bedford againſt the kinges will.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in of the graye friers.</note>In the .v. yeare of kinge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes raygne the gray fryers of the order of Fraunces came fyrſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Englande.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage into bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</note>In the .xiii. yeare of kinge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the thyrd he ſailed into bretayne with a noble army agaynſt Lewes kynge of Fraunce, wher after ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge of the countre a peace was concluded betwene the .ii. yonge Prynces.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the king &amp; his lordes.</note>In the .xvi. yeare of this Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges raygne, a variaunce kyndled betwene kyng Henry and hys lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:28"/> becauſe he put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſeruice Englyſhe men, and truſted ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers aſwell in his counſell as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices nere about him.</p>
               <p>In the .xix.<note place="margin">The king maried.</note> yeare kynge Henry toke to wyfe Elinour doughter of the Earle of Prouynce.</p>
               <p>Aboute the .xxi. yere of king he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the vniuerſite of Parys conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that no Preeſtes vnder paine of deadlye ſynne ſhoulde haue .ii.<note place="margin">No preeſt ought to haue .ii. be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefytes.</note> benefytes.</p>
               <p>In the .xxxi.<note place="margin">The liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don loſte.</note> yeare kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry ſeyaſed the Frauncheſſe of the citie of London for a Iudgemente ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a gaynſte a Wydowe named Margaret vyell. But ſhortly after they were reſtored.</p>
               <p>In the .xxxviii. yere prynce Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde,<note place="margin">The fyrſt prince of waies</note> eldeſt ſonne to kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry maryed Elynour doughter to the kyng of Caſtell to whome king Henry gaue the principalitie of Wales, and the gouernaunce of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:29"/> Gyen, and Irelande, whereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan fyrſte that the kynges of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ordayned theyr ſonnes prince of Wales.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile at ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</note>In the .xlviii. yeare of Kynge Henryes raygne greate varyaunce was betwene the kynge and hys Lordes and commons. In ſomuch that neare vnto Lewes kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and his barons fought a cruell battayle, where the kynge loſte the felde where the kyng himſelfe with Richarde his brother kyng of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and ſyr Edward his ſonne and other noble men to the nombre of .xxv. wer taken, of the commons were ſlayne .xx.M.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king delyuered oute of priſon.</note>The king and his brother wer deliuered vpon promyſe made to performe certayne Actes made at Oxforde in the parliament before, for ſuerty wherof Prynce Edward remayned as pledge.</p>
               <p>Shortly after fell great vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce
<pb facs="tcp:26821:29"/> betwene the Earle of gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and the Earle of Leyceter and Prynce Edwarde toke parte with the Earle of Gloceſter,<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at killing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthe</note> and at kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngworthe was foughte a cruell battayle the vyctory fell on prynce Edwardes parte.</p>
               <p>Shortlye after ſyr Symonde mounford Earle of Leceter gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a new army and mette Prynce Edward at Eueſham where Syr Symonde the Earle was ſlayne &amp; dyuerſe other that toke his parte.<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at Eueſham</note>
               </p>
               <p>About the .liiii,<note place="margin">The liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don loſte.</note> yeare of kynge Henries raygne was ſuch dyſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taken agaynſt the Londoners that the kyng ſeaſed theyr liberties into his handes. But after the citie by meanes of frendes payed a fine of .xx.M. Markes and ſo was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to theyr lyberty.</p>
               <p>In the .lv.<note place="margin">A voyage into the holy land</note> yeare of this kynge ſyr Edward the kinges ſonne toke his iourney into the holy land, and
<pb facs="tcp:26821:30"/> there he reſcued the citie of Acres whiche was beſeiged by the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan of ſurrey.<note place="margin">The deth of kinge henry the thyrde.</note> Duringe which voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>age Prynce Edward beyng in the holy land: kyng Henry hys father fell ſycke at Weſtminſter and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the .xvi. daye of Nouember, the yeare of Chriſt .M.cc.lxxiii. and is buried at Weſtminſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Edward the fyrſt.</head>
               <p>Edward the fyrſt of that name and ſonne to Henry the .iii. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hard of the death of his father came from the holye lande. And was crowned kynge at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minſter the .xix.<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes did ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>age to kynge Edward</note> daye of Auguſt the yere of chriſt .M.cc.lxxiii. At which tyme Alexander kynge of Scottes was preſente and did homage to kynge Edward.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lewellyn of wales.</note>In the ſeconde yeare of kynge Edwarde the Kynge wente into
<pb facs="tcp:26821:30"/> Wales and ſubdued Lewellyn Princes of Wales which paied to the kynge for a fine .l.m. Markes.</p>
               <p>In the .x. yeare of thys kinge Lewellyn Prince of Wales rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd,<note place="margin">A bataile in wales.</note> but after they purſued ſo the Welchemen that Lewellin and his brother Dauid fled, but after Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellyn was taken by ſyr Edmond Mortymer who ſmot of his heade and ſent it to the kynge, and after that his brother was hanged, dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and quartered.</p>
               <p>In the .xiii. yeare of this kinge,<note place="margin">The liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeaſed.</note> the king ſeaſed the liberties of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don into his handes becauſe the Mayre toke brybes of the bakers. And ſuffered them to ſell breade vnder the ſyſe.</p>
               <p>In the .xxiiii.<note place="margin">A bataile in ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> yere of kinge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Scottes dyuers tymes rebelled wherfore kynge Edwarde beſeiged the towne of Barwyke where was fought a cruell bataile,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:31"/> the vyctory fell to the Englyſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wanne the towne where were ſlayne of the Scotes .xxv.M. and after warde the kynge of Scottes ſubmitted him ſelfe to kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of England.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A battel at fankyrke.</note>In the .xxvi. yeare (kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being in flaunders (the Scot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes rebelled, and choſe them a newe kynge called Wales, and entred Northumberlande. But the nexte yeare after kinge Edward gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a great power and entred ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and at a place called Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerke, he mete with the Scottes where betwene them was foughte a cruell battayle, but at the ende the Englyſhmen had the victorye, and ſlewe of the Scotes to the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of .xxxii.M. and Walis theyr new choſen king fled in to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſes, and the common people yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to the kyng of England.</p>
               <p>About the .xxxii. yeare Edward
<pb facs="tcp:26821:31"/> the kinges eldeſt ſonne commytted dyuers ryots to the great dyſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of hys father wherefore the kynge enpryſoned his ſonne and other that were of his companye.<note place="margin">The king put his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in priſons</note>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo a bout the .xxxiii. yeare of kynge Edwarde the fyrſte Wales the Scot was taken and brought to London and there put to death.<note place="margin">A bataile in ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> Anone after many Lordes and biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Scotlande came and yelded them ſelues to kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. But Robert le Bruſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his oth rebelled agaynſte kinge Edwarde, and ſhortlye after the kinge with a great hoſte wente into Scotland where he met with Roberte le Bruſe at a place nyghe ſaynte Iohns towne where was fought a cruell batayle, the victory fell to the Englyſh men, and .vii.m Scottes were ſlayne, and Roberte le bruce fled to the kynge of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, and dyuerſe lordes were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:26821:32"/> who were ſent to London, and there put to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the fyrſte</note>In the .xxxv. yeare kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde fell ſyke and dyed the .vii. daye of Iulye, in the yeare of chriſt M.ccc.vii. and is buryed at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>⚹ Edwarde the ſecond.</head>
               <p>EDwarde the ſecond of that name, and ſonne of the fyrſt Edwarde and prince of wales, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne his Raygne ouer England the .xxiiii. day of February the yere of Chryſt .M.ccc.vii. and raygned xviii. yeres thys edward was faire of body but vnſtedfaſt of maners, and diſpoſed to lyghtnes. For he refuſed the companye of hys Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and men of honoure, and haun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a monge vylaynes and vyle perſones, he gaue him ſelfe alſo to ouer muche drynkinge, and lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:26821:32"/> wold diſcloſe thynges of great counſaile. And beſides that he was geuen to theſe vices of nature,<note place="margin">what yll counſayle maye doo</note> he was much worſe by the counſayle and famylyaritie of certayne euyll diſpoſed perſonnes, as Pierſe of Ganeſton, Hughe the Spencers, &amp; other, whoſe wanton counſayle he folowing gaue him ſelfe to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyte and pleaſure of the body, no thyng ordering his common weale by ſadneſſe, diſcreſion, and Iuſtice, whiche thinge cauſed fyrſte greate varience betwene him and hys no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſo that ſhortlye he became to them odible, and in the ende was depriued of his kingdome.</p>
               <p>This kinge in the ſecond yeare of his raygne,<note place="margin">The king maryed,</note> went into fraunce &amp; maried Iſabell doughter to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip le Belle kynge of fraunce, and after with her returned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
               <p>About this time Piers of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſton behaued hym ſelfe ylle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte
<pb facs="tcp:26821:33"/> the Lordes, and waxed ſo proude that he would reuyle them, wherfore they ſodenly roſe,<note place="margin">Piers of ganeſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be headed.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiged him in the caſtell of Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broughe, and at the laſt wan it and toke Piers and broughte him to a place nere to Warwike. and there ſtroke of his heade where with the kinge was greatly dyſpleaſed.</p>
               <p>About y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi. yere of this king, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert le Bruſe heryng of the deuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwene the king and his lords came agayne in to Scotland and there was amytted kinge,<note place="margin">A batayle at banoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes borne</note> wherfore kinge Edwarde prepared a greate Armye and wente in to Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and nere to a place called Banockyſbourne he mete with the Scottes where was betwene them a cruell battayle, but the Englyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men loſt the felde, and many of the lordes and great men of England were ſlayne and taken, and the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fledde wyth greate daunger into
<pb facs="tcp:26821:33"/> Barwyke.</p>
               <p>In the .ix. yeare of kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Scottes wan Barwike,<note place="margin">The ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes won barwike.</note> and ſhortly after they entered Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberlande and ſlewe man wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and chyld.</p>
               <p>Aboute this time there was a greate dearthe in Englande of all thinges,<note place="margin">Great pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in England</note> and after folowed greate Peſtilence, yet all theſe mocions mended not the kynge of his yll liuinge.</p>
               <p>In the .xi.<note place="margin">A bataile of mitton</note> yeare of this king the Scottes entred Englande &amp; at a place in yorke ſhire called Mitton was fought a cruell batayle where the Engliſh men loſt the felde, and much people of the countrey ſlaine But the kinge was all ruled by Hughe Spenſer the father and the ſonne, and the commons had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in great hatred.</p>
               <p>In the .xii. yeare of thys kinge
<pb facs="tcp:26821:34"/> there was a Parliament holden at London,<note place="margin">Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cers baniſhed.</note> where by the entreatinge of the lordes, Hugh Spencer the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and Hugh Spencer the ſonne were baniſhed the Realme. But it was not longe after but the kynge contrary to that ordynaunce made in the Parlyamente ſente for theſe Spencers agayne, and ſet them in hyghe aucthorytie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A batel at brough bryge</note>Shortly after the Lordes roſe agaynſt the kynge, and at broughe bryge the kynges Captayne called Andrew of Harkeley met wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where many of the Barons of eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande were ſlayne and taken, and afterward that the Earle of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter and dyuers other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and knyghtes were putte to deathe.</p>
               <p>In the .xvii. yeare of thys king the quene fearinge the tyrannye of the Spenſors,<note place="margin">The quen fled the lande.</note> fled wyth her yonge ſonne Edwarde into Fraunce to
<pb facs="tcp:26821:34"/> her brother Charles where ſhe and her ſonne was gentlye receyued of her brother, which made great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe to ayde her agaynſt the tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Spencers.</p>
               <p>Shortly after Charles the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kynge (fearyng the Manaſſyng of the byſhoppe of Rome) forſoke his ſyſters quarell,<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and her ſonne dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of fraunce.</note> and commaunded her to auoyde his lande.</p>
               <p>In the .xix.<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with her ſon en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered the lande.</note> yeare of kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, quene Iſabel and her ſonne by the ayde and helpe of ſyr Iohn of Heynalde, with a ſmall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of Heynowayes, retourned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England, to whome the nobles and commons gathered in greate nombre and purſued the kinge, the Spenſers, and other enemies, ſo narowlye that ſhortlye after they toke them, and kepte the kinge in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at kenelworth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spenſours, the Earle of Arundell, Robert bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docke, and other Tyrantes whiche
<pb facs="tcp:26821:35"/> of longe tyme had greued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reame were put to deth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Edward the thyrd.</head>
               <p>Edward the third of that name and ſonne to Edwarde the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and of Iſabell; onelye doughter of Phillip le Belle, after the depoſynge of his father, was crowned kynge the ſecond daye of February, the yeare of Chriſt .M.ccc.xxvi.<note place="margin">Of kinge Edwarde the thyrde</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was but .xv. yeres of Age. He was a man of excellent modeſtie and temperaunce, and ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunced ſuche parſons to hyghe dignities, as dyd moſte paſſe other in integrytye, and innocencie of lyfe. In feates of armes he was ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye experte, as the noble Prowes by him atchiued do well declare, as Froyſart and other wryters do declare at large. Of his lyberality and clemency he ſhewed many gret
<pb facs="tcp:26821:35"/> examples, brefelye, in all Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely vertues he was ſo excellente, that few noble men before his time maye be to hym compared. At his begynnynge he was chefelye orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſyr Roger Mortimer, and his mother Iſabell.</p>
               <p>In the fyrſt yere of his reygne,<note place="margin">The ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> the Scottes entered into England and the kynge with a greate powre came to them at the Parke of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope and beſet them rounde about, but by the treaſon of Syr Roger Mortimer the Scottes eſcaped without battayle wherby the king loſt that voyage &amp; al his charges.</p>
               <p>Shortly after at yorke the kinge maryed Phyllip the earles dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of Henaude.<note place="margin">The king maryed.</note> Then the kynge made peace with the Scottes and releaſed to them theyr homage, and delyuered vnto them their charter or indenture called Ragman,<note place="margin">Peace with the Scottes.</note> as it was ſayde by the counſel of the old
<pb facs="tcp:26821:36"/> Quene and ſyr Roger Mortymer which anone after was made Earle of Marche. And the old quene &amp; he toke vpon them the rule of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole realme whereby manye thynges grewe oute of order.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Therle of kente be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note>About the thyrde yeare of this kynge the Earle of Kente, the olde kynges brother, ſuppoſyng his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther had bene alyue deuyſed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne letters for the deliueraunce of his brother, wherfore he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, and by aucthoryte of parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament condempned and therefore was beheaded.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prince ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde borne.</note>In this yere was borne at Wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtocke Prynce Edwarde whiche in proceſſe of tyme grewe to a noble and famous man, and was in his dayes counted the floure of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualry throughoute all the worlde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Syr Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note>In the fourthe yeare of kinge Edwardes raigne, ſyr Roger Mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymer was accuſed for dyuerſe
<pb facs="tcp:26821:36"/> poyntes of treaſon, and namelye that he was ouer famylyar with the olde quene Iſabell the kynges mother for whiche accuſacions he was ſhortly after beheaded.</p>
               <p>In the .vi.<note place="margin">A voiage into ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</note> yeare king Edward went into Scotlande with a great power, and at a place called Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downe hyll, gaue the Scottes ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle wherin he optayned a tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant victory. So that he ſlewe of them .viii. Earles .ix.c. knyghtes and baronettes .cccc. eſquiers and xxxiii.m. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſoudyers: And of the Engliſhe men were ſlayne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye .xv. perſons at the ſame voyage he wan the towne of Edenbrough and Barwycke with manye other caſtels, and gaue the gouernaunce of Scotland to Edwarde Baylol, betwene whome and the Scottes were foughten manye batayles, with greate dyuerſite and chaunge of fortune.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:37"/>
               <p>After this time the Scottes ſo often rebelled,<note place="margin">Scotland ſuffered muche pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury.</note> that kynge Edward made .iii. voyages into that lande within the ſpace of .iiii. yeares. And with great manhode alwaye van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſhed his enemies, and cauſed them to ſwere to him feautlie, and homage. In theſe battayles were ſlayne wel nere all the nobylyty of Scotlande, with infinite nombre of the common people.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande and Fraunce.</note>In the .x. yere king Edward clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med tytle to the crowne of fraunce, wherfore open warre was proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med betwene Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and fraunce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">good they vitels in England</note>Aboute this time (as Fabyan wryteth) by reaſon of ſcarſite of Mony, was ſuch plentie of vitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in Englande that the lyke had not bene ſene. For a quarter of wheat was ſolde for .ii. s. a fat goſe for .ii. d. a pygge for a peny a fate Oxe for .vi. s. viii. d. a fat ſhepe for vi. d. or .viii. d. vi. Pygions a peny.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:37"/>
               <p>In the .xii. yeare king Edward prepared ſtronglye to make warre in to Fraunce,<note place="margin">King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warpe where he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the empire</note> and for ſure ſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente of Amite betwene hym and the Holenders, Selanders, &amp; Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banders, ſayled to Antwarpe wher he concluded the matter with hys alies and by the conſent of the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour Lewes, was proclaymed vicer geneneral of the Empyre.</p>
               <p>In the .xiii.<note place="margin">The king held a par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liamente.</note> yeare kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward returned into England and called his parliament at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter, and there by the aduyce of the whole realme, toke vpon hym the tytle to be kynge of Fraunce, and ioyned the armes of Englande to the armes of Fraunce and bare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quarterlye as they yet continue, at which parliamente was graunted greate ſommes of mony to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne hym in his warres.</p>
               <p>In the .xiiii.<note place="margin">A batel on the ſea.</note> yeare of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes raygne, he ſaylyng toward
<pb facs="tcp:26821:38"/> Flaunders nye to the hauen of Scluce, met with the French kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges nauye: where was foughte a cruell batayle, whereof the kyng of England had the victory, and the frenche fleete, that was in nombre cccc. ſayle, was wel nere all deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Soudiers taken, ſlaine, and drowned, ſo that of .xxxiii.M. there eſcaped not one.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A yeare for one yeare.</note>Shortlye after kynge Henry with a myghty army both of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and of the Empyre, entered fraunce, and beſeiged Torney, but ſhorlty after (by the meanes of the countes of Henand) mother to the Quene of Englande and ſyſter to the french kyng, a peace was made for .xii. monethes, and kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward returned into England.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes trobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande,</note>In this tyme the Scottes (by the ſettynge on of the frenche men) recouered a great part of that land and in moſte cruell wyſe vexed the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:38"/> Englyſhe garyſons.</p>
               <p>In the .xviii. yeare,<note place="margin">The order of the gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter fyrſte ordained,</note> kinge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde enuented and ordained firſt the order of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> garter at Winſoure.</p>
               <p>Aboute this time the Earle of Darby was ſente into Gaſcoyne where he wonne dyuers townes &amp; Caſtels,<note place="margin">Gaſcoine wonne.</note> and before Anberoche the Earle of Darby, by polecy of ſyr Walter of Manni, with a .M. eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhemen diſcomfited and ſlewe .x.M. frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Gaſcoines, and toke pryſoner the Earle of Lay, their chefe capitayne, with dyuers other nobles: &amp; ſubdued the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre.</p>
               <p>In the .xx. yeare king Edward with his ſonne Prynce Edwarde, ſayled into Normandy, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode and ſpoyled the countre, euen to Paris, and gathered wonderful rycheſſe and prayes which he ſente into Englande. Shortlye after he encountred the Frenche kynge nye to the foreſt of Creſſy,<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of Creſſy.</note> wher betwen
<pb facs="tcp:26821:39"/> them was foughte a cruel batayle, and kinge Edwarde obtayned the victorye. In that battayle was ſlayne the floure of the Chiualrye of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. That is to ſay the king of Boheme, with ten other greate Princes, foure ſcore barons .xii.c. knyghtes, and mo than .xxx.M. of the common Soudiers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Callys wonne.</note>After thys victorye the kynge wente towarde Calys and beſeged the towne the ſpace of .xi. monethes during which ſege the french kyng came to rayſe the ſege but ſhortlye after he departed without battaile, wherfore they of Callys yelded vp the towne to kinge Edward.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king of ſcottes taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</note>In the tyme of the ſeige before Callys, Dauid of Scotlande by the ſettinge on of the french kinge, warred on the borders of England But the quene aſſembled a ſtrong armye, as well of preeſtes as laye men, and nere to Durham toke in batayle the kinge of Scottes pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:39"/> with manye of his greateſt Lordes and earles, and ſlew of the common ſoudiers .xv.M.</p>
               <p>About the .xxii.<note place="margin">A greate derth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough out all the worlde.</note> yeare of kynge Edward the .iii, ther was a wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful famyn and Peſtilence raygned throughout all the world. In Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſcant the .x. perſon of an .c. was lefte on lyue. In the citie of parys in Fraunce died .L.M. and in the citie of London (beſyde the bodies buried in churches and churche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes, and monaſteryes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of buriall) there was buryed in the charterhouſe churche yerde .l.M. perſons and aboue, as wryteth Fabian.</p>
               <p>In thys yeare the Captayne of Callys conſpyred to betraye it agayne to the Frenchemen,<note place="margin">calis like to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed.</note> the hiſtorye whereof declareth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully the great manhode, polly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, liberalytie, &amp; gentylneſſe of the noble kinge Edwarde, reade Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarde
<pb facs="tcp:26821:40"/> the .c. and .v. Chapter of his fyrſte boke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The tira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the byſhop of rome. &amp;c.</note>Aboute this time kinge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was elected to be Emperour But he conſyderynge the trouble &amp; vnquietneſſe of the byſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, refuſed it. And then they choſe the Marques of Meſſena whiche alſo refuſed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gines yel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to the engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>In the, xxvii. yere of king Edwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des raygne the towne and caſtel of Gines was yelded to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> engliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voyage into Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyne.</note>In the .xxix. yeare of kinge Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes raygne Prynce Edwarde of Wales, with a ſtronge compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of Soudyers paſſed into Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyne, where he made ſore warre, &amp; deſtroied Caſtelles and townes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hym with greate ſucceſſe and toke the Caſtell &amp; towne of Rehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morentyne, with other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voyage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note>Aboute this tyme king Edward ſayled to Calys, &amp; began to make war vpon frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but ſhortly after
<pb facs="tcp:26821:40"/> he returned becauſe the Scottes roſe &amp; inuaded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Englyſh borders.</p>
               <p>In the .xxx.<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile of poytiers.</note> yeare of kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes raygne prynce Edward of Wales, nie to the citie of Poytiers ioyned batayle with king Iohn of fraunce, on whome the prynce wan a noble victory. In this conflycte kynge Iohn was taken wyth hys yonge ſonne Phillippe,<note place="margin">The fifth king take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryſoner.</note> there were taken .ix. earles, the archebyſhop of Sens, and many other greate lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Baronettes and knyghtes &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of name to the nombre of .xvi.c and there were ſlayne the Duke of Burgoyne, the Duke of Athens, ſyr Iohn Cleremond Marſhall of Fraunce, with many lordes, Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netes, knyghtes, and menne of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to the nombre of .xvii.c. and iii.M of other meane perſones. And after this felde thus wonne, the Prynce with his pryſoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to Burdeaux. And ſhortely
<pb facs="tcp:26821:41"/> after they ſayled in to Englande where they were of kinge Edwarde noblely receyued.</p>
               <p>In the, xxxiii. yeare, kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde with the Prynce his ſonne wetne to Calys and ſo in to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce where he made ſharpe warre,<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> and burned and deſtroyed the countre without mercye. But ſhortly after by great entreaty ther was a peace concluded on this condicion that kinge Edward ſhould haue to his propre poſſeſſion the countres of Gaſcoyne and Guyan, Poyters, Lymoſyn, Beleuile, Exanctes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys Guines, and diuers other lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyps, townes, Caſtels and all the landes to them belonging, without knowledge of any ſouerainte,<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch king raun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſomed.</note> obey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunce, homage, or ſubiection for the ſame, and that the french kyng ſhoulde paye for his raunſome .iii Myllons of Scutes, whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounte to .v.c.M. li. and ſo kynge
<pb facs="tcp:26821:41"/> Iohn was delyuered.</p>
               <p>In the .xxxvii. yeare of kinge Edwarde,<note place="margin">The deth of the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch king</note> kynge Iohn of fraunce came into englande of his fre wyll to ſporte hym and had greate chere. And ſhortly after dyed at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy at London.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo Prynce Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde toke poſſeſſyon of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Guyen and Acquitaine and did homage to his father for the ſame.<note place="margin">Prince ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de duke of Guyen.</note>
               </p>
               <p>About the .xl. yeare of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Dampeter of Spayne was expulſed his realme by his baſterd brother Henry, wherfore he fled to Prynce Edward whych was then at Burdeaux.<note place="margin">A bataile i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spaine.</note> But this Peter by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayde of Prynce Edwarde fought with his brother Henry and put him to flyghte and ſlue .v.M. of his men. And reſtored Peter to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe cities and holdes which he be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore had loſte. But not longe after
<pb facs="tcp:26821:42"/> the Prynce returned home, and he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry repayred his army, and warred vpon his brother ſo fearſelye that in the end he vtterly vanquiſhed hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deth, and then without reſiſtence poſſeſſed the kingdom of Spaine.</p>
               <p>In the .xlii. yere of kyng Edward new varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwen Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> wherfore the duke of La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſter was ſent with an army into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; nere vnto Arde the Duke of Burgoyne lodged within a mile of the Englyſh armye the ſpace of xviii. dayes and neuer profered ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, but at the laſte ſtole awaye pryuelye by nyghte, and then ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Duke further into fraunce as Froyſar ſheweth at large.</p>
               <p>In the .xliii. yeare, ſyr Roberte knolles entered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with a ſtronge army and waſted &amp; deſtroyed the countrie and paſſed euen by Parys ranged in batayle, and without any notable battayle
<pb facs="tcp:26821:42"/> returned.</p>
               <p>About the xlv. yeare the french men made ſharpe warre in Gyen,<note place="margin">Great va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riaunce i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gaſcoine</note> and many dyuers ſkyrmyſhes wer betwene the frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh men but moſt commonlye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the englyſhemen loſte, and the citie of Lymoge &amp; other cities rebelled againſt Prince Edward. Wherfore Prynce Edwarde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuinge all this, &amp; what for lacke of money, and what for ſykenes &amp; maladyes that he had, he departed into England, leuyng behynd him hys bretheren the Duke of Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the Earle of Cambryge, to rule Gaſcoyne, but ſone after they came into Englande.</p>
               <p>In the .xlvi.<note place="margin">A ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> yeare of kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes raygne the Earle of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke was ſent with a great army to fortefye the towne of Rochell. But he was met on the Sea, wyth a companye of Spanyardes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene
<pb facs="tcp:26821:43"/> whome there was a cruell fyghte, but the Engliſhe men were diſcomfited, and the earle of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke was there taken wyth a .c.lx. mo priſoners, and the moſt parte of his men ſlayne and drowned. And ſone after the towne of Rochel was yelded to the Frenchmen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note>Alſo in the .xlvii. yere the duke of Lancaſter landed at Calys with a myghtye armye paſſed throughe fraunce robbyng and ſpoylyng the countre eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Burdeaux, and wer neuer fought with ſaue onelye at a ſcirmyſhe they loſte .l. Speres and xx. archers.</p>
               <p>In the .l. yeare of this kynge there was ſuche ſyckenes and mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talite,<note place="margin">A greate deathe.</note> as well in Italy as in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innumerable of people died</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of Prince Edwarde</note>In the .li. yere Prince Edward of Englande departed out of this lyfe who was in his time the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Chiualry and was buryed at
<pb facs="tcp:26821:43"/> Canterburye.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the ſame yeare, the .xxi.<note place="margin">The deth of kinge Edward</note> daye of Iune, the yeare of Chryſte a .M.ccc.lxxvii. kynge Edwarde dyed and is buryed at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. This king Edwarde when he dyed had .iiii. ſonnes, that is to ſay Lyonell Duke of Clarence, Iohn of Gaunte Duke of Lancaſter, Edmonde of Langley Duke of yorke, and Thomas of Wedſtocke Earle of Cambrege.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Rychard the ſeconde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ichard the ſeconde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, and ſon to Prince Edward eldeſt ſonne to kyng Edward the thyrd beyng of .xi. yeres of age was crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned kynge of England the .xv. day of Iuly, the yeare of Chryſte a .M ccc.lxxvii.</p>
               <p>In the fyrſt yeare of kyng Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardes
<pb facs="tcp:26821:44"/> raygne the frenche kynge ſente a great nauy to the ſea,<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch men ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> which entered in dyuers partes of thys realme and dyd moch harme wher they landed, and at the laſte came into Thames, &amp; ſo to graues ende, and brent parte of that towne and returned into fraunce agayne.</p>
               <p>About this tyme the Earle of Cambrege the kynges vncle was ſent into fraunce with .viii.M.<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and paſſed the water of So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, and ſo forth to Troyſe and wan it, and ſo paſſed to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre of Gaſcoine, and ſo into Brytayne where ſyr Iohn of Mounford duke of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne gladly receyued them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iacke Strawe.</note>In the .v. yeare of this kynge the commons of Englande aroſe and ſpecially in Eſtſex and Kente, and made them capytaines of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chefe they called Iacke ſtraw, which came into the towre of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don where the king was, and there
<pb facs="tcp:26821:44"/> they toke the Archebyſhop of Cau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terbury, the Lorde of ſaynt Iohns, and a frere the kinges confeſſoure, and at the towre hyll ſmot of theyr heades, and ſlewe and robbed all ſtraungers in Sothewarke, and brente the Duke of Landcaſters place called the Sauoy, and dyd muche hurt, and beynge aſſembled in Smithfeld, vſed them ſelues ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye proudely and vnreuerentlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kynge. But by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode and wyſdome of Wyllyam Waulworth mayre of London, that rude company was diſceuered and theyr Capitayne Iacke ſtraw was ſlayne.<note place="margin">Iacke Strawe ſlayne.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Aboute thys tyme was a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull great earthequake in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande the lyke whereof was neuer ſene before that day nor ſyns.<note place="margin">A greate erthquak</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the .vii. yeare of kynge Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,<note place="margin">A voyage into flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</note> Henry Spenſer biſhoppe of Norwitche wente into Flaunders
<pb facs="tcp:26821:45"/> at the commaundement of the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome with a great power, and wan Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kyrke and grauelyn, and brente .xl. ſhyppes and muche goodes beyng within them, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there fell a diſeaſe of the flickes and other dyſeaſes among his ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, that he was fayne to returne into Englande.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king maryed.</note>In the .viii. yeare kynge Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Maryed the doughter of Viceſlaus, Emperour of Almaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A bataile on the ſea</note>In the .x. yeare of this king the earle of Arundell was ſente into Guyan to ſtrengthe the ſoudyers there, but on the ſea, he met with a flote of Flemynges laden with Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chell wyne, and ſet vpon them and toke them. Amonge the which was taken the Admyral of fraunce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Great va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the king &amp; his Lordes &amp; commons</note>In the .xi. yeare there was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous greate trouble and dyſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon in Englande, betwene the kinge and his counſayle and other
<pb facs="tcp:26821:45"/> nobles and prelates of the realme. The commons by the ayde and comforte of the kinges vncles and other lordes of the realme (that is to ſaye the Duke of Gloceſter, the duke of yorke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earles of Darby, of Arundell, and of Notyngham) put to death dyuers of the kynges counſel and chefe offycers, and cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the duke of Ireland and other out of the realme, for that they cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the kynge to burden his people with exactions and could make no iuſt accompt of the ſame when they were required.</p>
               <p>In the .xv.<note place="margin">The liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don loſt.</note> yeare there was a ryot in London wherfore the king ſeaſed the lybertye of the citie into his handes. But ſhortlye after by the meanes of the quene, &amp; doctor Graueſend biſhop of London they were reſtored to theyr lybertyes.</p>
               <p>In the .xviii.<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> yeare king Richard made a voyage into Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which
<pb facs="tcp:26821:46"/> was more to his charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honor.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the iiii. bany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note>In the, xxii. yeare Henry Boling broke duke of Hareford, and ſonne to the Duke of Lancaſtre, and the duke of Norfolke were banyſhed out of the realme.</p>
               <p>Shortly after Henry bolinbroke Duke of Herford,<note place="margin">Kinſh Ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chard the ii. depoſed</note> wich was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, beyng ſente for of the Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doners, came into englande with a ſmall power, to whome the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons gathered in ſo gret multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; forſoke their Prince, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not longe after at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtel of Flint, they toke king Richard, &amp; held hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoner in the tower of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where he yelded vp &amp; reſigned to the ſayd Henrie duke of Hereforde, all his power &amp; kingly title to the crowne of england &amp; fraunce, knowleging that he was worthilye depoſed for his demerites and miſgouernynge of the common weale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:46"/>
               <head>¶Henry the fourthe.</head>
               <p>HEnry the fourthe, ſonne to Ihon of Gaunt, late Duke of Lancaſter, and thirde ſonne of Edwarde the thyrde toke poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his realme of England the laſt daye of Septembre, in the yere of oure Lorde a .M.ccc.lxxxxix.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i .M.ccc.lxxxix. Anno primo Henrici .iiii. Thomas knol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Grocer mayre. William Hyde Ihon Walderne ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare dyed kynge Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde the ſeconde. In thys yere alſo certaine Dukes and Erles of England and other,<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ci againſte the kyng.</note> were accorded to make a mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming on twelfe daye at nyghte, trayterouſly to kyll the kynke, than beynge at Wyndſore, whiche beynge warned therof, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſodaynelye &amp; came to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, &amp; made purſute after the ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:26821:47"/> conſpiratours, which apprehended and taken, were after by the lawe put to deathe. In this yeare kyng He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry ſent ſyr Thomas Perſy Erle of Worſiter with a goodly crue of ſoudiers into Aquitayne to ayde ſyr Robert knowlles leuetenaunte there,<note place="margin">A vyage into aqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne.</note> and to parſwad the people to theyr obeyſaunce, who dyd greatly ſtomacke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of king Richard</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente.</note>In this yeare was enacted by auctorite of Parliamente, that no Lorde, nor other man, myght gyue anye gownes, or lyueryes to anye of theyr tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or other perſons, onelye but to theyr houſehold and menyall ſeruauntes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo was enacted that all repyers,<note place="margin">An other acte.</note> &amp; other fyſſhers from Rye, Wynchelſee, and other coſtes of the ſea ſyde, ſhoulde ſell theyr fyſſhe theyr ſelfe in Cornehil Chepe, &amp; other ſtretes of London, to all men that woulde by theim,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:47"/> Fyſſhemongers, and all other that woulde bye the ſayd fiſſhe to make ſale agayne of it, onely except.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .M.cccc. an. ii. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici .iiii. Ihon Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces goldſmith mayre, Ihon Wakele, Wyllyam Ebot, ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the French kyng ſent Lorde Iames of Burbone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> xii.C.<note place="margin">the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made a vyoage into Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande.</note> knyghtes &amp; ſquyres to ayd Owen Glendor a ſquyre of wales agaynſt kynge Henry, and landed at Plummouthe in Deuenſhyre, who ſhortly after to his great loſſe &amp; ſhame retired backe into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</p>
               <p>In thys yeare a Priour &amp; viii. fryers were ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged at Tiburne for treaſon.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.i. anno tertio, henrici quarti. Ihon Shadworth Mayre, Wyllyam Fremyngham, Wylliam Venour ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was ſene in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande<note place="margin">a blaſing ſtarre.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26821:48"/> a comete or blaſynge ſtarre of a huge quantite.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.ii. anno quarto herici quarti. Ihon Walcot mayre Robert Chicheley, Richarde Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſhereffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was the battayl of Shrowyſbury.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.iii. an quinto henrici quarti. Wyllyam Aſkam mayre. Thomas Fawkener, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Pole ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in yorke ſhyre</note>In this yeare began a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocion in Yorke ſhere, but theyr entente was knowen, and for that treaſon was apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Richard Scrope Archebyſhop of Yorke, the Earle Marſhall. Syr Ihon Lampley, and ſyr Robert Plumton, who in whytſon weke were beheaded at Yorke.</p>
               <p>In this yere the king of Scottes
<pb facs="tcp:26821:48"/> ſente hys ſonne the Prynce into Fraunce,<note place="margin">The pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryſoner.</note> but by violence of wether was dreuen into Englande where he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynued priſoner many yeares after.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.iiii. an. vi. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici iiii. Ihon Hynd draper mayre, William Louth, Steuen Spilma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.v. an. vii. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quarti. Ihon woodcoke mayre Henry Barton, Wyllyam Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.cccc.vi. an. octauo henrici quarti, Rychard wittyngto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marcer mayre, Nicolas Wotton, Geffery Broke ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶An. do. M.cccc.vii. an. ix. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici quarti, William Sandon mayre,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:49"/> He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry Balton, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fret ſhyref.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.viii. an. x. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quarti, Drewe Bare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmythe Mayre, Thomas Duke, Wyllyam Norton ſheryffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.ix. an. xi, henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci quarti, Rychard Marlow Yrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger mayre. Ihon Law, Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chichelye ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xii. anno he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci quarti. Thomas knolles grocer Mayre, Ihon Penne, Thomas Pyke ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare was a byll put into the Parliament agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, for waſting of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poraltie.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc xi. an. xiii. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quarti. Robert Chichelye gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer mayre, Ihon Reynwel, Walter Cotton ſhyreffes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:49"/>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xii. an. xiiii. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quarti, Wylliam Walderne marcer Mayre, Raufe Leuyngha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Wylliam Senenoke ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare kynge Henry the fourth dyed, the .xx. daye of march,<note place="margin">The deth of Kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the fourthe.</note> In the yere of our lorde a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cccc.xii. And whan he had reygned xiii. yeares fiue monethes, and one and twenty dayes, &amp; lyeth buryed at Cantorbury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Henry the fyfte.</head>
               <p>HEnry the fyfte began hys reigne the xxi. day of march, in the yeare of our lord next aboue mencioned. And was crowned at weſtmynſter the nynthe daye of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryll folowynge. In the yeare of oure lorde M.cccc. and xiii.</p>
               <p>In thys yeare was a generall counſel holden at Conſtance vpon the ryuer of Reyne,<note place="margin">a general counſell.</note> to the whyche councell was ſente Rycharde Erle
<pb facs="tcp:26821:50"/> of warwike and iii. Biſhopes with dyuers doctours knyghtes &amp; ſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nombre of viii.C. horſes.</p>
               <p>In this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel were condempned to death for hereſy Ihon Wicliffe, Ihon Huſſe, &amp; Ieram of Prage,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The lord cobha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of hereſy.</note>In thys yeare ſyr Ihon Olde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtell lorde Cobham was accuſed to the Archebiſhop of Cantorbury for certeyne poyntes of hereſy.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xiii. an. i. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quinti, Wyllyam Walderne mayre, Raufe Leuingham, Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seuenoke ſheyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xiiii. an. ii. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quinti. Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Crowner maire Ihon Sutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ihon Michel ſhyre.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Ley<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceter.</note>In this yeare in Apryll was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den a Parliamente at Leyceter, in the which Parliament were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded many profitable lawes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other thynges was a byll
<pb facs="tcp:26821:50"/> put into the Parliamente houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thacceſſe of the ſpiritualtye &amp; was lyke to take effecte, but than the Biſhoppes and Abbottes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the kynge to make warre in to Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his title there, ſo that in al his tyme after he had neuer leſer to ſpeake therof more. And alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde that voyage was graunted by the ſpiritualtie ſuch a payment as had not bene payed before.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xv. an. tertio henrici quinti, Thomas Fakener mercer mayre. Ihon Mychel, Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Alayne ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yere the kinge dyd prepare an armye into Fraunce of .xv.C.<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the kyng.</note> ſhyppes, &amp; the day before he ſholde depart from Southha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton certaine lordes dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpyre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges death for the whiche conſpiracie was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended Rychard Erle of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brege, the lord Scrope, &amp; ſyr Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gray knight, who at the tyme
<pb facs="tcp:26821:51"/> of theyr executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed that they were ſet a worke by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kyng. And after theyr execution the king ſet forwarde, &amp; on the vigill of the aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of our Lady he with all hys nauy landed at Kyd Caux in Normandy.<note place="margin">The win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of Herflew.</note> And on the next daye he beſeged the towne of Herflwe, and the .xxxvii. daye after the ſayd towne was yelded to the kyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of agi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> courte.</note>In this yeare in Octobre was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battell of Agyn courte whiche vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory by the onely prouiſion of god fell to the Engliſhemen, for kynge Henry had in his bataile but onely two .M. horſemen and xii.M. fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temen of al ſortes. And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch partie were almoſt all the nobilitie of Fraunce with .lx.M. hortemen beſyde fotemen. There were ſlayne on the Frenche partie aboue .x.M. perſones wherof were princes and nobles bering baners .C.xxvi. and all the remnaunt ſauynge .xvi C.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:51"/> were knyghtes, Eſquires, &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen. And on the Engliſhe parte wer ſlaine Edward duke of yorke, therle of Suffolke, ſyr Rycharde Kykeley and Dauy ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me eſquyre, and of al other not aboue .v. or .vi C. perſons.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xvi. an. iiii. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici quinti, Nicolas wotton dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per Mayre, Wyllyam Cambridge Alayne Euarde ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Maye the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror Sigiſmond came into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande to treate of a peace betwene kynge Henry and the French king and was nobely receyued but hys labour toke ſmall effecte.<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me into Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yere was Harflew beſeged by the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chemen,<note place="margin">Harflew beſeged.</note> both by water &amp; land, but inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent the kyng ſent his brother the Duke of Bedforde with a noble army &amp;,<note place="margin">A battell on the ſee</note> on the ſea en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered the French Nauy in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre
<pb facs="tcp:26821:52"/>
.v.C. ſhyppes, whiche were by the Engliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyſcomfyted and almoſte all taken or drowned, and when the army by lande knew that the Nauy by ſea was diſcomfited, reyſed theyr ſege and departed.</p>
               <p>¶An. do. M.cccc.xvii an. quinto henrici quinti, Henry Barto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Mayre, Robert Whityngton, Ihon Couentre ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage into Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</note>This yeare in Iuly the kynge accompanied with his brethren the Dukes of Clare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and Glouceſter with a noble armie made a voyag into Normandy and wonne Caen with the caſtell and in concluſyon what by force &amp; rendering vp wan almoſt all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holdes in Normandy. ¶Anno domi. M.cccc.xviii. anno vi. henrici quinti, Richarde Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe yremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger mayre, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry Rede, Ihon Gedney ſhyrefes.</p>
               <p>In this yere ſyr Ihon Oldcaſtel
<pb facs="tcp:26821:52"/> knyght lorde Cobham was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in cheines and after brente.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the laſte daye of Iuly the cytie of Roan was beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged bothe by water and by lande,<note place="margin">The citie of Roan beſeged.</note> inſomoche that by reaſon of famin they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to fall to treatie and ſo the xix. daye of Ianuary the cytie was yelded to the kynge. And immeniatly after all Normandy yelded them ſelues alſo.</p>
               <p>¶An. do. M.cccc.xix. an ſeptimo henrici quinti, Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seuenoke grocer mayre, Ihon Parues, Rauf Barton, Ihon Bryan ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In the tyme of thys warre in Fraunce there was great variau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene the nobles of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſpecially betwene the Dolphin,<note place="margin">variau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene the lordes of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> the Duke of Burgon, and the Duke of Orliaunce with other, and there was a place appoynted to mete to treate for a peace and thether came
<pb facs="tcp:26821:53"/> the Dolphin &amp; the Duke of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne and the ſayd Duke kneling on his knees tellyng his tale to the Dolphin one Tavagny du chaſtel ſmote the Duke on the heed with a hachet &amp; ſo moſte ſhamefully was mordered.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nycatyon for a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note>In this yeare there was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munycatyon for a peace betwene England and Fraunce but it toke ſmall efecte, wherfore the Kynge went forward with his conqueſt &amp; ſent an armie to Ponthoyſe &amp; with forſe wanne it,<note place="margin">Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thoiſe wonne.</note> to the great feare of the pariſience and all Fraunce.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xx. anno viii. henrici quinti, Richard whitingha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mercer mayre, Robert whitingham Ihon Butler ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A peace concluded betwene Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; England</note>In this yeare in Maye was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded a peace betwene the Kynge of Englande and the French kyng ſo that king Henry did mary lady
<pb facs="tcp:26821:53"/> Katheryne the Frenche kynges doughter at Troye in Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paigne after which mariage kynge Henry was proclamed heyre and regente of Fraunce.</p>
               <p>In this yeare at Chriſtmas the kyng of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kept ſuch a noble houſe in Roan as Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that to his courte all men reſorted and fewe to the Frenche kynges courte, and after Chriſtmas he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaned his brother y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Cla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence his leuetenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t generall both of Fraunce &amp; Normandy, and on the morow after candelmas daye the kynge and the quene toke ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng at Calis &amp; landed at Douer and on ſaynte Mathues daye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge the quene was crowned at weſtminſter.<note place="margin">the kynge returned into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xxi. an. ix. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quinti, Wylliam Cambrydge grocer mayre, Ihon Butler, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam weſton ſhyreffes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:54"/>
               <p>In this yere the Duke of Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made a rode into Aniowe where by a lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bard he was betraied and ſo was ſlayne with dyuers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men more.<note place="margin">the death of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</note>Alſo in this yeare in Maye the kynge paſſed the ſea with a noble army into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and purſued the dolphin on ſuch wyſe that he coude ſcant fynde any place to hyde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the kyng beſeged the cytie of Meaux in brye during whiche ſyege was borne at Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore the kynges ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne named He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry.<note place="margin">the byrth of Kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the ſyxte.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xxii. an. x. hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici quinti, Robart Chychelye gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer mayre, Rychard Ioſtlyn, willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weſton ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of Kynge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the fyfte.</note>In this yeare kynge Henry the fyfte dyed the xxi. daye of Auguſt. In the yeare of oure Lorde next a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mencioned whan he had reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:26821:54"/>
.ix. yeares and fyue monethes and xxiiii. dayes, and lyeth buryed at Weſtmynſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Henry the ſyxt.</head>
               <p>HEnry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vi. began his reigne the fyrſt day of Septembre, in the yere of our lorde next aboue mencioned, &amp; was crowne at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynſter in the eyght yeare of hys reygne, all whiche tyme before for inſufficiency of age he was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of his vncles, the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of Bedforde and Gloceſter, he was of the age of viii. monethes &amp; odde dayes and not aboue.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.xxxiii. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no primo Henrici ſixti. Wyllyam walderne mayre, William Eſtfeld Robert Taterſale ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare was the Duke of Gloceſter made protectour of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande, and the Duke of Bedforde
<pb facs="tcp:26821:55"/> rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which Regent like a noble capitayne maytayned the warre againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dolphin ſo longe as he lyued.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxiiii. anno ſecondo Henrici ſixti, Wyllyam Crowner drapen Mayre, Nicolas Iames, Thomas wadford ſhyref.</p>
               <p>In this yere the Duke of Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of vernoyle.</note> made warre vpon the Dolphyn of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and vnto Engliſhemen fell the victory at the battayle of vernoyle where were viii.M. Frenchmen ſlayne.</p>
               <p>Alſo in this yeare was Iames Steward kynge of ſcottes delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red which was priſoner in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d long time before,<note place="margin">The king of ſcottes deliuered.</note> who for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d did omage to the king of Englande and maryed the lady Iane doughter to the Erle of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet and coſyn to the kynge.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini M.ccc.xxv. an.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:55"/> tercio Henrici ſixti, Ihon Michell Mayre, Symon Seman, Ihon Bythwater ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the Duke of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter protecter of Englande ſente vnto hys brother the Regente of Fraunce .x.M. men to mayntayne warre agaynſt the Dolphin.<note place="margin">A voiage into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo was a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at vernoyle in perch betwene the Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; the Duke of Alau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſon,<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of Vernocle in Perch</note> the victory fell to the Englſhe men where were ſlayne of Frenchmen &amp; Scottes .ix. thouſand and vii.C. and of Englyſhemen xvi.C.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini M.cccc.xxvi. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no quarto Ihon couentre marcer Mayre Wyllyam Mylted, Ihon Brokeley ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In thys yeare began a greate variaunce in Englande betwene the noble men of the realme for the Byſhop of wyncheſter dyd enuye<note place="margin">Of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prelat</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26821:56"/> the lorde protector in ſo moch that the Lorde Regent of Fraunce was fayne to come into England to ſet theim at one.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxvii. anno quinto Henrici ſixti. Ihon Rayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well fyſhmonger Mayre, Roberte Arnold, Ihon Heygham ſhyrefes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxviii. anno ſixto Henrici ſixti. Ihon Godney draper Mayre, Robert Ocle, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry Frowyke ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Orliance beſeged.</note>In thys yeare was Orlyaunce beſeged by the thenglyſhe men and as ſyr Ihon Faſtolfe wente frome Parys towarde the army with vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales ther met him an army of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemen where after longe conflicte the Englyſh men optained the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory where were .xxv.C. Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlayne and .xii.C. taken priſoners.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:56"/>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxix. anno ſep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>timo Henrici ſixti. Henry Berton ſkiner Maire, Thomas Duſhous Raufe Holande ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the ſeage brake vp before Orliaunce and wan many townes as Geneuile, Meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Fort, with diuers other, and as the lorde Talbot was coming to Meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with v.M. men he was incountered with an army of Frenchmen to the nombre of xxiii.M. where was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners the Lorde Talbot &amp; the lorde Scales with other.<note place="margin">The lord talbot ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken priſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner.</note> And of Engliſhemen were ſlayne xii.C. perſons to the great reioyſynge of the Dolphin &amp; other of his facte.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo after this vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory the Dolphin reyſed an army &amp; wan by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſicion Troys in Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payne, &amp; the cytie of Raynes with dyuers other townes and caſtelles whiche Dolphin had in his campe one Ione a ſtout Ramp whiche the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:57"/> Frenchemen dyd call La puſell de dwe,<note place="margin">Of Ione the witch</note> the mayd of God. And after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde in thys ſame yeare was the Dolphin ſacred kynge of Fraunce at Raynes in the preſenſe of all the noble men of his faction,<note place="margin">The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred king at Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> and the Dukes of Lorayne and Barre by the name of Charles the ſyxte.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The duke of Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth the Dolphyn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place.</note>And the Duke of Bedford Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Fraunce beynge at Paris hard of this doinges of the French king with an noble army of Engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Normans purſued him frome place to place tyl he came to ſenles in Berre where both armies might ſe other, &amp; after bothe armyes had lyne in eche others ſyght .ii. dayes, the Frenche kyng lyke a carpet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitayne in the dead of the nyghte brake vp his army &amp; fled to Braye which when the Regent perceyued myſtruſtynge the waueringe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s returned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his armi to paris.</p>
               <p>In this yere by the procurement
<pb facs="tcp:26821:57"/> of the byſhop of Rone Henry Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Cardinall of Wyncheſter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the ryche Cardinall,<note place="margin">Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſente into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</note> was ſent into Beame with iiii.M. men to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the biſhop of Rome, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came to Douer he was countermaunded by the lorde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector &amp; went into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to helpe the Regent agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kyng.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini M.cccc.xxx. anno octauo He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eſtfeld mercer Mayre. Wyllyam Ruffe, Raufe Holande ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere the Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce lefte the gouernaunce of Paris to the Byſhop of Ely Chaunceller of Fraunce,<note place="margin">A parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente at Roan.</note> and the ſayd Regent held Parliament at Roan animatynge the Normans to their obeyſaunce to the Kynge of Englande &amp;.c. At which ſeaſon the Frenche king ſent the Duke of Alaunſon and his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres Ione, the greate goddeſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:58"/> the Frenche men to ſcale Paris,<note place="margin">A ſealeng of parys.</note> from the which they were beaten to theyr great loſſe &amp; theyr capytayne Ione was throwne into the dykes &amp; had much worke to ſaue her lyfe.</p>
               <p>In this eyght yeare kyng Henry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixt was crowned at wiſtminſter.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxi. an. nono Henrici ſyxti. Nicolas Wauton Mayre. Water Charſy, Roberte Large ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The order of the gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den flece.</note>In this yeare did Phillip Duke of Borgon mary Lady Iſabell doughter to Ihon kynge of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale and great aunt to the king of Englande, at whiche maryage the ſayd Duke ordeyned the order of the golden flece.</p>
               <p>In this yeare in Decembre the Englyſhmen beſeged the towne of of Laigny in the whiche the puſell was capitayne with other, who iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued oute to ſkyrmyſhe wyth the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:58"/> Englyſhemen and Burgonyons, at which ſkyrmiſhe Ione the puzel was taken and after was ſente to the duke of Bedford to Roan wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>after long examinacion was brent to aſſhes.<note place="margin">Ione the puzel bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at Roan.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxii an. deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Ihon Welles gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer Mayre. Ihon Aldryle, Steuen Browne ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this ten yeare kynge Henry the ſyxte was crowned at Paris,<note place="margin">king he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the ſyxte crowned Kynge of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Paris.</note> which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe cytie in all frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with great triumphe &amp; nobilitie.</p>
               <p>After kyng Henry was crowned kynge of Fraunce he kepte a noble houſe fyrſte at Paris and after at Roan in whiche tyme there was a peace concluded for vi. yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Englyſhemen and the Frenchemen,<note place="margin">A peace co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded.</note> whiche peace within ſhorte tyme by the Frencheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was broken.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxiii. an. xi.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:59"/> Henrici ſixti. Ihon Perueis fyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger Maire. Ihon Olney Ihon Paddiſly ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>In this yere the peace in Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was broken wherfore on both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes were armyes ſet forthe &amp; tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fortefied, and when the French men coulde not preuayle they ſente forth theyr accoſtmed ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mayſter Treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and corrupted Piers Andebeuffe conſtable of the caſtle of Roan with mony, that the Marcial of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with ii.C. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons diſgyſed dyd entre the caſtell of Roan but they were ſone eſpyed &amp; ſo ſome of them were ſlayne ſome hanged and ſome rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſomed at the Regentes pleaſure.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxiiii. anno xii. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Ihon Brokely dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per mayre. Thomas Challo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ihon Lynge ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the commons of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:59"/> Normandy made inſurrection, by the ſettyng on of the Frenche kyng but thei were ſhortely ſuppreſſed,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons of norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy rebelled.</note> &amp; many of them ſlayne.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was Ihon Duke of Burbon delyuered out of pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche had bene pryſoner in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſyns the butayle of Agyncourt xviii. yeres before,<note place="margin">The duke of Burbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delyuered out of pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.</note> &amp; paied for his rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome xviii.M. pound ſtarling.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo began a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaunce betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and the Duke of Burgoyne to the loſſe of Englande and no gayne to Burgony.<note place="margin">A variau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce betwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent &amp; the Duke of burgoine</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xxxv anno xiii. Henrici ſixti. Robert Ocley grocer Mayre. Thomas Barnewel Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Eyre ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yere was a great froſt that endured from the feaſt of ſaint ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theryne vnto the feaſt of ſaynt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentyne,<note place="margin">A greate froſte.</note> ſo that neyther ſhyp might ſayle nor botte be rowed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer
<pb facs="tcp:26821:60"/> of Thames, &amp; therfore all the vyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage was caryed to Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by land in Cartes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A peace be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; the duke of Burgo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yne.</note>In this yeare was concluded a peace betwene the Frenche kyng &amp; the duke of Burgoyn to the great dyſpleaſure and loſſe of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhemen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente of Fraunce.</note>In this yere died the noble Duke of Bedforde Regent of Fraunce &amp; lyeth buried in our lady churche at Roan, in whoſe ſted was elected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente of Fraunce Richarde Duke of Yorke.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxvi. an. xiiii. Henrici ſixti. Henry Frowyke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer Mayre. Thomas Catworthe, Robert Clopton ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">paris loſt</note>In this yeare the Pariſſioners rebelled agaynſt the Engliſhemen and ſo rendered vp the cytie of Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris in to the Frenchemens handes and ſlew many of the Engliſhmen
<pb facs="tcp:26821:60"/> that kept the cytie.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the Duke of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goyne with an army of xl.M. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd laye ſeage to Calys.<note place="margin">Calis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeged.</note> And du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge this ſeage the Duke ſent the lorde of Croy with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my to laie ſege to Gines,<note place="margin">Gines be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeged.</note> who gote there but ſmall gaynes.</p>
               <p>Shortly after it was noyſed in the campe of the Duke, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord protector of England was ſhipped with a great army to come to calis to rayſe the ſeage, and ſodaynly in the nyghte the Duke of Burgoyne rayſed his ſeage &amp; lykewyſe ſent to Gynes for the lorde Croy &amp; lyke a valyante capitayne fled awaye by nyghte and on the next daye in the mornyng the lorde protector came to land &amp; entered the campe of hys enemyes, but they were gone,<note place="margin">The duke brake vp his ſeage &amp; fled by nyght.</note> and had left behynde them the Tentes, ordinaunce, and vitayles, and all that they had.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:61"/>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxvii. an. xv. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Ihon Michell mayre, Thomas worſted, Wylliam Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gore ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxviii. an. xvi henrici ſixti. William Eſtfeld mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer Mayre. Wylliam Chapman, Wylliam Hales ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The erle of warwi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke made Regent.</note>In this yere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Erle of warwyke was made Regent of Fraunce and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke of Yorke diſcarged, which Erle after hys ariuall in Fraunce dyd many noble feates as Halle wryteth at large.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xxxix. an. xvii. Henrici ſixti Steuen Browne gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer Mayre. Hughe Duke, Nicolas Yeo ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A darthe in engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note>In this yeare by reaſon of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperat wether there was a great derthe in Englande ſo that wheate was at .iii. ſhyllynges .iiii. pens a buſhell, &amp; all other graynes were
<pb facs="tcp:26821:61"/> ſold at an exceſſiue price, aboue the olde cuſtome.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xl. an. xviii. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Robert Large mercer Mayre. Robert Marſhall, Philip Malpas ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere the Duke of Yorke was made againe Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which accompanyed with the Erle of Oxford and dyuers other noble men ſayled into Normandy,<note place="margin">the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che kyng fled for feare.</note> &amp; he hearynge that the Frenche kynge laye at ſeage at Ponthoyſe wente thether with a noble army. But the Frenche king hearing of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe mennes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge breake vp his ſeage &amp; went awaye by nyght.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was the Duke of Orliaunce delyuered out of pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who had bene pryſoner in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d xxv. yeares,<note place="margin">The duke of orlian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red oute of pryſon</note> and for his raunſome the Duke of Burgoyne paied iiii. C. M. Crownes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xli. anno. xix.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:62"/> He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Ihon Paddiſly gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmyth Mayre, Ihon Sutton wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam wetinghale ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this xix. yeare many noble feates of armes was do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Yorke lord Regent ſent the lorde Wylloughby with a noble Crue of archers and men of warre into Pecardy which did va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyantly.<note place="margin">Thre ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes at ones in Fraunce.</note> Alſo he ſent the lord Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot to beſeage Depe, &amp; he himſelfe acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with the Duke of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet ſet forward in to the duchye of Aniowe where he dyd many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table feates.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xlii. anno xx. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Robert Clopto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mayre William Combra, Richarde ryche ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the ſteple of Paules churche in London was ſet on fyre by lyghtnynge.</p>
               <p>In this yere alſo began to kindle in Englande the fyre of malis, for
<pb facs="tcp:26821:62"/> the Cardynall of Wyncheſter dyd enuy the gouernaunce of the lorde protector,<note place="margin">A vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Lordes of England.</note> for which variaunce af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many a noble man, as after ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xliii. anno .xxi. Henrici ſixti. Ihon Atherley yron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger Mayre, Thomas Bemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Rycharde Nordon ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xliiii. an. xxii. Henrici ſixti. Thomas Catworthe grocer mayre. Nycolas Wyfolde, Ihon Norman ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare all the prynces of chriſtendome ſent theyr Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors vnto Troyes in Champayne to treate for a peace betwene Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande &amp; Fraunce,<note place="margin">A treatie for a peas</note> and a peace was taken for v. yeares.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xlv. an. xxiii. Henrici ſixti. Henry Frawyke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer mayre. Steuen Foſter, Hughe
<pb facs="tcp:26821:63"/> Wyche ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare Lady Margret the kynges doughter of Ceryll was maried to the kyng,<note place="margin">The king maryed.</note> and after crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned at Weſtminſter, whiche mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was neyther profitable to the Realme, nor yet honorable to the kyng, as Halle declareth at large.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xlvi. an. xxiiii. Henrici ſixti, Ihon Olney mercer Myre. Ihon Herot, Godfrey Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layne ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at norwitch</note>In this yere was a great inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in Norwyche agaynſte the Prior of Chriſtes churche for ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of new fines of their tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the cytezens kept the gates againſt the Duke of Norfolke, who came thether to appeace the matter, but in concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they opened the gates &amp; ſubmitted them ſelfes. The chefe offendours were put to execution, and the Mayre dyſcarged of hys
<pb facs="tcp:26821:63"/> offyce, and ſyr Ihon Clyfton was made gouernour tyll the kyng had reſtored the cytezens to thyr lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties agayne.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.xlvii. an. xxv. Henrici ſixti. Ihon Gidnes draper Mayre, Wylliam Abraham, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Scot ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare dyed the good duke of Gloceſter, and is buried at ſaint Albones.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.xlviii. an. xxvi. Henrici ſixti. Steuen Browne gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer Mayre. Wyllyam Cantlowe, William Marow ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the Englyſhemen loſt many townes in Fraunce,<note place="margin">The begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge of norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy.</note> for by cauſe of the varyaunce betwene the nobilitie of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, there was ſmall prouydyng to ſend ayd into Fraunce ſo that the ſowdiers were vnpaid to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great loſſe of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do m.cccc.xlix. an. xxvii.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:64"/> Henrici ſixti, Thomas Challton Mayre. Thomas Canynges wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Holyn ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Roan yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Frenche kynge.</note>In this yeare was Roan yelded to the Frenche kynge by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Cytezens rebelled agaynſte the capitaines and ſo did almoſt al the townes of Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy, and for lacke of ayde the Duke of Somerſet &amp; the lorde Tolbot were fayne to ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre all into the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voyage in to Irelande</note>In this yeare alſo the Duke of Yorke was ſent with a conuenient army into Irelande to be the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges leuetenaunt there, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the wylde yriſhe who dyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rebell.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.l. anno xxviii. Henrici ſixti. Nicolas Vyuold gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer mayre. Wyllyam Dere, Ihon Myddelton ſhyreffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voyage into Fraunce.</note>In this yeare was ſyr Thomas Kyriel ſent into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with a M. and v.C. men, and as he with other
<pb facs="tcp:26821:64"/> capitaines we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reſcue Caen they met with a great army of Frenche men, &amp; after longe fyght the french me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obteyned the victory, and there were ſlayne iiii.M. Englyſhemen and viii.C. taken priſoners. This was the fyrſt foughten felde that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Frenchemen gate of the Englyſhe men in many yeres before,<note place="margin">The fyrſt felde loſte by thyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhmen.</note> therfore I can not blame them though thei make moche of it, they ſet forth all &amp; hyde nothyng that maye be foud to theyr glory, but they wryte not how many of them were ſlaine and deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. m.cccc.li. Anno. xxix. Henrici ſixti. Wyllyam Gregory ſkynner maier, Mathewe Philip, Chriſtopher warton ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>In thys yere the Englyſhemen loſte all the holdes and townes in normandy which were in Engliſh mens poſſeſſion xxx. yeares before,<note place="margin">Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy loſte.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26821:65"/> and where conquered by kyng He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the fyfte.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lii. anno xxx. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſixti. Gefrey Feldyng mayre Richard Lee, Richard Allay ſhyre.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling peace</note>This yeare was a metyng of a great hooſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brent heth in kent, betwene the Kynge and the Duke of Yorke, and other noble menne whyche was appeaſed for a tyme and the malyce diſſimuled.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine was wonne by the french menne.</note>In this yeare was the countre of Aquitayne won by the frenche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which had ben Englyſh .iii c yeares and odde yeares and was wonne by Henri the thyrde.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.liii. anno. xxxi. Henrici .vi. Ihon Norman draper mayre. Ihon Walden Thomas Coke ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtelon.</note>In thys yeare the Lorde Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot Erle of Shreweſbury recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the cytye of Burdeaux and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conquered manye townes in
<pb facs="tcp:26821:65"/> Gaſcoyne And at the Batyle of Chaſtellon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide noble Erle was ſlayne and his ſonne alſo, with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe noble &amp; valyante Captaines of Englande, and many taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. Of this noble Earle of Shreweſbury ſerche Halles Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycle and you ſhall perceyue hys vaylyaunt actes.</p>
               <p>Thys yere Mahomet the great Turke wan Conſtantinoble with exceadynnge greate ſlaughter of Chryſten people,<note place="margin">Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople wonne by the greate Turke.</note> and vnto the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſment of the Turkyſh empire.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.liiii. an. xxxii. Henrci ſixti. Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Foſter mayre. William taylont, Iohn feld ſhir.</p>
               <p>This yere the flambe of Enuie bruſte oute betwene the Duke of Yorke, who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> claimed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crowne,<note place="margin">The fyrſt bataile of ſaynete Albons.</note> and the Duke of Somerſet, who ruled the kynge, and at Saynt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans was fought a cruell batayle
<pb facs="tcp:26821:66"/> and vnto the Duke of Yorke fell the victorye, &amp; on the kinges parte was ſlayne the Duke of Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, the Earle of Northumberland, the Lord Stafforde with .viii.M menne more. After this bataile the duke of yorke with gret reuerence brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king to London where the ſayd Duke was made Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure of the realme.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lv. an. xxxiii. Henrici .vi. Wyllyam Marlowe grocer mayre. Iohn yonge Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas oldgraue ſhiryffes.<note place="margin">The duke of yorke depoſed of his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tectorſhip</note>
               </p>
               <p>By meanes of the quene and her counſell the Duke of Yorke was depoſed of hys protectorſhyp whiche thynge was cauſe of a new grodge and malys.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lvi. an. xxxiiii Henrici .vi. Thomas Chaninges mayre. Ihon Stuard, Raufe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Riot in Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>In this yeare was a great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot
<pb facs="tcp:26821:66"/> committed in London againſte the Lombardes and Italians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Mercers ſeruaunte was caſte in pryſon for ſtrykynge an Italyon.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lvii. an. xxxv. Henrici ſixti, Godfrey bolayne mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer mayre. William Edward, Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Reynere ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare the french menne perceyuynge the dyſcorde in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande ſent .ii. nauies into englande &amp; one of them landed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> downes and they (hauyng knowledge that the people of Sandwitch were fled the towne for death) cam and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the towne wyth great crueltye.<note place="margin">Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied by the french<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the cytye of Mens in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many was the ſcyence of Printing fyrſt inuented by one named Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanes fauſtius.<note place="margin">whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and where the ſcience of printinge was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lviii. an. xxxvi
<pb facs="tcp:26821:67"/> Henrici ſixti. Thomas Scot dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per mayre, Raufe Ioſteline, Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Nedham ſheryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A fayned peace.</note>In this yeare was made a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned peace betwene the kinge and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene and theyr counſell on the one party, and the Duke of Yorke with hys confederates on the other partie whiche agremente endured not longe.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lix. an. xxxvii. Henrici ſixiti. Wyllyam Hull fyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger mayre. Iohn Stocket, Iohn Plummer ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel on blor Heath.</note>In this yeare was the batayle on Blore heathe in Shropſhyre betwene the Lorde Audeley on the Kynges partye, and the Earle of Salliſbury on the Duke of yor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes partye, where the victory fel to the Earle of Salliſburye, and the Lorde Audley was ſlayne, and his army dyſcomfited.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:67"/>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lx. an. xxxviii. Henrici ſixti. Richarde Lee grocer mayre. Iohn Lambert, Rycharde Fleminge Sheryffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere the Duke of yorke aſſembled a great Army of northre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men and welchemen,<note place="margin">The duke of yorke flede.</note> and the Earle of Warwike came with a great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre from Calis, &amp; nere vnto Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawe in the Marches of Wales they pytched theyr felde, &amp; towarde them came the Kynge accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Dukes, of Somerſet and Exeter with a myghtye Army, and the nyghte before the batayle Andrew Trollop fledde frome the Duke to the Kynge, wherfore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght the Duke hym ſelfe fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ireland and the Earles of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſbury, Marche, and Warwyke, fled into Deuinſhere &amp; ſo to Calis.</p>
               <p>After this departing the Duke of Yorke wyth hys confederates were proclamed traytours,<note place="margin">The duke of yorke ꝓclamed traytour</note> and the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:68"/> yonge Duke of Somerſet was made Captayne of Calys but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came there he could not be recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued bycauſe the erles was there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſo he was fayne to take Gynes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle of north ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note>In this yere alſo the Earles of Marche, and Warwicke came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Calys, and ſo landed at Sande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch, and ſo came to London and by the way met them dyuers noble men and ſo came to London wher they were gentlye receyued and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long conſultinge the ſayde Ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les with an Army of .xxv.M. men ſet forward to mete the kynge who hadde prouyded an Army nere to Northehampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where was fought a cruell battayle, the victory fell to the Earle of March, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany where were ſlaine on the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges partye the Duke of Bokyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and the Earle of Shrewſbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with .x.M. tall Englyſhmen &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26821:68"/> the reſte fled and lefte the kynge a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone, and the Duke of Somerſet,<note place="margin">The king taken.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quene, &amp; her ſonne fled into the Biſhopryke of Duram.</p>
               <p>After thys felde the Earle of March conuaied the Kinge to Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don wher was a Parliament ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned at whiche Parlyament the Duke of Yorke was made ayre apparent and all his progenye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hym.<note place="margin">The duke of yorke proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ayre apparent</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yere Quene Margaret in greate haſt gathered a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Northren me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and at wake feld in a cruell fyghte diſcomfited and ſlew the Duke of Yorke,<note place="margin">The ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at wakefeld</note> with his ſon the Earle of Rutland, &amp; the earle of Saliſbury was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, who afterward was beheded at Pomfret &amp; his heade ſent to yorke.</p>
               <p>The Quene with her retinewe nere to ſaynte Albons diſcomfited the Earle of warwike and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Norfolke,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at ſainct Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons.</note> and delyuered Kynge
<pb facs="tcp:26821:69"/> Henry her huſband, in this battell was ſlayne .xxiii.c. men and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue of whome no noble men is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred but ſyr Iohn Gray who the day before was made Knyght.</p>
               <p>After thys battayle the kynge and the Quene (heringe of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng of the Earle of Marche and Earle of Warke with a great nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of Marchemen) toke theyr ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Norwarde and the ſayd Earle came to London, where Edwarde Earle of Marche by the conſent of the nobylytie and commons was proclaymed Kinge the .iiii. daye of Marche in the yeare of our Lord M.cccc.lx. by the name of kynge Edwarde the fourth.<note place="margin">kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamed kynge.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Immediatlye after kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde was proclaymed kynge he purſued Kynge Henry towarde yorke and met wyth King Henries Armye at a place called Towton wyth whome he had then a cruell<note place="margin">The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle at towton</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26821:69"/> battaile but Kynge Edwarde had the victory, In the feld were ſlaine xxxvi.M. and .vii.c. perſones and all Englyſhemen. Alſo there was ſlaine the Earles of Northomber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande and Weſttmerlande, the Lorde Clyfford, and diuerſe other and Kynge Henri loſt all and was fayne to flee the lande after he had raigned .xxxviii. yeares and .vi. monethes.</p>
               <p>After this cruel batayle kinge Henry fledde into Scotlande and Quene Margeret with the yonge Prynce fled to her father the duke of Anges.<note place="margin">king He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Edwarde the .iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nno dommini .M.cccc.lxi. anno primo Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di quarti. Hugh Wiche mayre. George Ireland, Iohn Locke ſheriſſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:70"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</note>This yere the .xxix. daye of Iune was kinge Edwarde the .iiii. wyth great tryumphe crowned at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynſter.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. M.cccc.lxii. anno ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condo Edwardi quarti. Thomas Coke mayre. Bartilmewe Iames, Wylliam Hampton ſheryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A bataile at Exha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>In thys yeare Kynge Henry and Quene Margaret hys wyfe came out of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a great Army of Frenchemen and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and in Exam ſhyre the Lorde Mountacute (gouernoure of the Northe countre) mete hym with a noble armye where Kynge Henry was diſcomfyted and fled, and the Duke of Somerſet (who a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forſoke Kynge Edward) was taken in the chaſe wyth dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who afterward wer beheaded.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .M.cccc.lxiii. an.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:70"/> tercio Edwardi quarti. Mathewe Philip gold ſmith maire. Thomas Muſcham, Robert baſſed ſhiriffes</p>
               <p>In this yeare kyng Henry came out of Scotlande into Englande by what meanes I haue not read,<note place="margin">Kyng hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry taken pryſoner.</note> but I thyncke not well ſtablyſhed in his wit but boldly he entred the Realme and aſſone as he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred he was knowen and taken by one Cantlow and brought toward the kyng whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyke met on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way by the kynges commaundement &amp; brought hym throughe London to the Towre &amp; there he was layed in ſure holde. And Quene Margret &amp; her ſonne departed out of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into fraunce where ſhe remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Duke Rayner her father tyll ſhe toke her infortunate iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into Englande agayne.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxiiii. an quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:26821:71"/> Edwardi quarti, Raufe Ioſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyne draper mayre, Iohn Tate, Iohn ſtone ſhiriffes,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed.</note>This yere the Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyke was ſent into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to treat of a Mariage betwene the Lady Bona, doughter to Lewes Duke of Sauoy and ſyſter to the French Quene, which mariage was a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto, but in meane ſeaſon kyng Edward maryed preuely at Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton the Lady Elizabeth, late wyfe of Syr Iohn Graye, for whyche mariage roſe greate varience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the kynge and the Earle of Warwycke hys chiefe frende and maynteynoure.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxv. anno quinto Edwardi quarto. Raufe Freney mercer mayre,<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of a doughter</note> Henry Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Wyllyam Conſtantine ſhyrif.</p>
               <p>In this yere the Quene was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered of a fayre Ladye and was
<pb facs="tcp:26821:71"/> named Elyzabeth whyche after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was wife to the noble prince kynge Henry the .vii. and mother to kynge Henry the .viii.</p>
               <p>Alſo in thys yeare was graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a licence that certaine cotſehold ſhepe ſhoulde be tranſported into Spayne,<note place="margin">A lycence graunted to carye ſhepe into ſpayne.</note> whych haue ſo ther mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied &amp; encreaſed that it hath tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the commoditie of Englande muche to the ſpaniſhe profyte.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxvi. anno ſexto Edwardi quarti, Iohn yong, grocer knight mayre, Iohn Brice, Iohn Browne, Iohn ſtotton ſhyr.</p>
               <p>In thys yere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baſtard of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon came into Englande to treate for a mariage betwne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earle Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reloyſe yeyre of Borgoyne,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> betwen t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of burgoyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; the Lord Scales</note> &amp; kyng Edwardes ſyſter whyche mariage was concluded. At whych tyme the ſayde baſterd chalenged the Lorde Scales for certayne feates of war
<pb facs="tcp:26821:72"/> whiche were done in Smethfelde, but the lord ſcales had the victory.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini .m.cccc.lxvii. an. ſeptimo Edwardi quarti, Thomas Owlgraue mayre. Humfrey hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Thomas ſtalbroke ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxviii, an. octauo Edwardi quarti, Willyam Taylour grocer mayre, Symon ſmith Wyllyam Heriot ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>In thys yere began the Earle of Warke to Rebel agaynſt kinge Edward and procured to hys part the Duke of Clarens brother to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge,<note place="margin">The earle of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eld.</note> the Archebiſhop of yorke, &amp; the Marques Mountacute hys brethren, whiche Earle with the Duke of Clarence wente to Calys where the ſayde Duke maried the Earles doughter of warwike.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Banbury helde.</note>In thys yeare alſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of yorkeſhyre made inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb facs="tcp:26821:72"/> at the ſettynge on of the Earle of Warwyke and hys adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes and made them a Captaine called Robyn of Ryddeſdale, and nere vnto Banbury the Lord Har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert Earle of Penbroke and hys brother ſyr Richarde harbert wyth an Army of .vii.m. Welchmen met the Northren men betwyxt whome was a cruell Battel where the nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren men optayned the victorye, &amp; the Earle of Penbroke &amp; his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Richard taken and beheaded, and .v.m. Welchmen ſlaine.</p>
               <p>After thys victory the Northre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men wente to Warwyke where the Earle,<note place="margin">King Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> and the Duke of Clarence had gathered a greate Army, and kyng Edward wyth his puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce came agaynſt them, but ſodenly in the nyght the Earle ſet on the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges campe, ſo that kynge Edward was there taken pryſoner, and ſo ſent to Middelham caſtel in yorke
<pb facs="tcp:26821:73"/> ſhyre to be kept wyth the Archbiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of yorke the Earles brother.</p>
               <p>Shortely after kinge Edward (hauynge frendſhip of his kepers) was ſuffered certayne dayes in the weke to ryde a huntyng and by the meanes of ſyr wyllyam ſtanley,<note place="margin">king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered oute of pryſon.</note> ſyr Thomas of Borogh, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other hys fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des with a great bond of men was reſcued from his kepers, and ſo delyuered oute of Pryſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Loſecote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felde.</note>Kynge Edwarde after he was come to Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gathered together hys Army, and ſo met wyth the Lorde Welles, with a great army, the victory fel on the kynges parte where were ſlayne .x.m. men at the leaſt, where were taken and behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Lorde welles, ſyr Roberd Welles his ſonne,<note place="margin">The lord welles be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>headed.</note> ſyr Roberd De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocke wyth dyuers other, thys ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle was called Loſecotefelde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:26821:73"/> the Lyncolne ſhyre men dyd worle away theyr cotes and ranne awaye.</p>
               <p>This yere the Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyke with the Duke of Clarence perceyuyng theyr partie weakened fled into fraunce for ſocoure where they taryed not paſt .vi. monethes.<note place="margin">Therle of warwike fled into Fraunce.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of Clarence,<note place="margin">Therle of warwike landed</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of Warwyke, Penbroke and Oxforthe landed at dertmoth, to whome by meanes of proclamaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made in kynge Henries name the commons gathered to them in greate nombre ſo that kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fearynge hys parte fled into Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Burgoine<note place="margin">kynge ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fled flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</note>
               </p>
               <p>After kynge Edwards fleing, diuers of his frendes toke ſaync<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary,<note place="margin">Kynge ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the v. borne in ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuarye.</note> and in eſpecially Quene E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſabeth who was porely deliuered in the ſainctuary at Weſtminſter, of a ſonne named Edward.</p>
               <p>Then was Henry the .vi. ſet at
<pb facs="tcp:26821:74"/> large and agayne proclamed king by meanes of the Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyke,<note place="margin">king hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his kynglye eſtate.</note> and other, and king Edward proclamed vſurper of the crowne but that contynued not longe.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxix. anno nono Edwardi quarti, Richarde Lee grocer mayre Robart Draper Rychard Gardener ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxx. anno decimo Edwardi quarti. Iohn ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton mercer knyghte mayre. Iohn Croſby, Ihon Ward ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere alſo kyng Edwarde hauynge kynge Henri in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany met with the Earle of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyke on Eſterdaye at Barnet .x.<note place="margin">Barnet felde.</note> myles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> London where betwene them was fought a cruell battayle the victory fell on kynge Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des parte where were ſlayne Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde
<pb facs="tcp:26821:74"/> Neuel Earle of Warwike, and the Marques mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacute his brother with .x.m. men more.</p>
               <p>Shortly after this bataile quene Margaret with her ſonne landed at Waymouth in Dorſetſhere, and when ſhe heard of the death of the Earle of Warwike, ſhe and her ſonne toke ſaynctuary at Beweley in hamſhyre, &amp; vnto her reſorted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of Somerſet, and the Earle of Deuenſhire with other,<note place="margin">A bataile at Tew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſburye.</note> who ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered a greate Army, and kynge Edwarde with a greate Army met with them nere vnto Tewkeſbury where was fought a cruel bataile, but kynge Edward had the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye where quene Margaret was ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken pryſoner, and Prince Edward her ſonne alſo, who in the kynges preſence was ſhamefully mourde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, this batayle was foughte the iiii. day of maye on a ſaterday, and on the mondaye after was behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:26821:75"/> at Twekeſburye Edmonde Duke of Somerſet the Prior of ſaynct Iohns Ieruſalem, with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other, and the Quene ſent pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoner to London, who afterwarde was redemed by her father, and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſent into fraunce.</p>
               <p>After this the baſterd Faucon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge who was made feſe Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall by the Earle of Warwike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a newe commocion with ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſhe men,<note place="margin">A new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mocion.</note> and eſexmen, who ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye was apprehendyd and put to deathe.</p>
               <p>In this yeare alſo vpon the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencion euen nexte folowinge the dead corps of kynge Henri the .vi. was brought from the Tower of London to Poules where he laye all nyghte.<note place="margin">The deth of kynge henry the vi.</note> But howe this Prince came to his deathe there be dyuers ſayinges, but commonly it is ſaid that Rychard Duke of Gloceter kynge Edwardes brother ſlewe
<pb facs="tcp:26821:75"/> hym wyth a dager.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxi. anno xi. Edwardi quarti William Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grocer mayre, Iohn Aleine Iohn Shelley ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxii. anno. xii. Edwardi quarti, William Hamp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton fyſhmonger mayre. Thomas Bledlow Iohn Browne ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.cccc.lxxiii. an. xiii. Edwardi quarti. Iohn Tate mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer mayre, wylliam Stocker Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bylleſdon ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxiiii. an. xiiii. Edwardi quarti. Roberte Drope draper mayre. Edmond ſhaa, Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Hyll ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare kynge Edwarde wyth a noble armye wente in to fraunce but afterward, conſidering the vniuſtnes of the duke of Bour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gone)
<pb facs="tcp:26821:76"/> there was a peace concluded ſo that the french kyng ſhould pay to kynge Edwarde .lxxv.M crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">A voyage into fraunce.</note> and yearly .l.M. crownes du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge kynge Edwardes lyfe.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.cccc.lxxv. an. xv. Edwardi quarti. Roberte Baſſet Salter mayre. Roberte Colwyche, Hugh Bryce ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere were diuers Bakers of London ſette vpon the Pillorye for makynge of lyghte weyghte of breade.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxvi. an. xvi. Edwardi quarti, Raufe Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelyn draper mayre, Rychard Rau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, Wylliam Horne ſheryffes.</p>
               <p>This yere from Crypylgate to Byſhopiſgate, London wale was newlye repared.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxvii. anno.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:76"/> xvii. Edwardi quarti. Humfrey Heyforde goldſmyth mayre, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Colet, Iohn Stocker ſheryffes.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare George Duke of Clarens yonger brother to kynge Edwarde beynge pryſoner in the tower of London was there drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a barell of Malmeſy.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.cccc.lxxviii. an. xviii. Edwardi quarti, Rycharde Gardyner mercer Mayre Robert Harding Robert Bifelde ſheryffes</p>
               <p>In this yeare was great mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie in London and throughout all England.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. m.cccc.lxxix. an. xix. Edwardi quarti. Bartilmewe Iames draper mayre. Thomas Ilam, Iohn warde ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxx. anno xx. Edwardi .iiii. Iohn Browne
<pb facs="tcp:26821:77"/> mayre, wyllyam Bacon, wyllyam Daniel ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. M.cccc.lxxxi. an. xxi. Edwardi quarti. Wyllyam Heriot draper knight mayre, Robert Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, wyllyam wykyng Richard Cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king made a feaſte to the maire of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>This yere in the moneth of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye the kynge ſente for the mayre wyth certayne of his brethren, and comeners of the cytye of London, vnto the Foreſt of waltham, and there cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> game to be brought before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that they ſawe courſe after courſe, and manye dere bothe redde and falowe ſlaine. And after that the king commaunded his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycers to brynge the mayre and his company vnto a pleaſaunte lodge made al of grene bowes, and there ſet them to dyner and ſerued theim wyth manye denty dyſhes and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wynes good and plenty, and
<pb facs="tcp:26821:77"/> ouer that cauſed the lorde Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlyn with other Lordes to chere the mayre and his companye ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye tymes whyle they were at dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and at theyr departynge gaue vnto them venyſon greate plentye.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare alſo the kynge ſene vnto the mayreſſe of London and her ſyſters the Aldermens wifes, two hartes .vi. Buckes, &amp; a Tonne of wyne, to make theym merye wythall.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxii. an. xxii. Edwardi quarti. Edmonde ſhaa goldſmith mayre, Iohn Mathew, William whyte ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>In the begynnynge of the .xxiii. yeare the .ix. day of Apryl, dyed the noble kynge Edwarde the .iiii. at weſtminſter and is buryed at win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, leuinge after him two ſonnes, that is to ſay Prince Edward his eldeſt ſonne and Richard Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:78"/> yorke, &amp; .iii. doughters, Eliſabeth that after was Quene, Cycili and Katherine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Edward the fyft.</head>
               <p>EDwarde the .v. beganne hys reygne ouer the realme of eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land the .xi. daye of Apryll in the begynnynge of the yeare of our Lorde .M.cccc.lxxxiii. the ſame Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde beynge of the age of .xi. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or there aboute, this Edwarde was neuer crowned but ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murthered by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of Rycharde the thyrd that after was kynge of englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Richard the .iii.</head>
               <p>RIchard the .iii. began hys do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynion ouer the Realme of England y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxi. day of Iune, in the yeare of oure Lord .M.cccc.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:78"/> lxxxiii. and the .vi. day of Iuly the nexte folowinge, was crouned at Weſteminſter.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxxiii. an. primo Richardi .iii. Robert billeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don haberdaſher mayre, Thomas Norlande, Wyllyam Martyne ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>In thys yere was the Duke of Buchyngham beheaded at Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſburye.<note place="margin">The duke of boking<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno. do. m.cccc.lxxxiiii. anno. ſecondo richardi .iii. Thomas Hyl mayre. Thomas Bretayne Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Cheſter, Raufe Auſtreye ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>This yere the .xxii. day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt in the yere of our Lorde.<note place="margin">boſworth felde.</note> M.cccc.lxxxv. was the Bataile of Boſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worth nere to leceſter in the which kynge Richard the .iii. in the third yeare of his reygne, was ſlayne by
<pb facs="tcp:26821:79"/> kynge Henri the vii. the whyche in the ſame daye began his reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Realme,<note place="margin">King hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry the .vii crowned.</note> and the .xxx. day of Octobre next folowing was crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned at Weſtminſter.</p>
               <p>In the .xiii. daye of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">Two mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res of lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don in one yeare and both died of the ſweate.</note> in the yere of oure Lorde laſte before mencioned dyed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweate the foreſaid Thomas Hille mayre in whoſe place the .xxiiii. day of the moneth and yere of our lorde laſte before mencioned, wyllyam ſtocker knyght, was choſen mayre, whiche Stocker dyed the .viii. daye of the ſayd moneth alſo of the ſweate, and the .xix. day of the ſayde moneth of September, was Iohn warde choſen mayre, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vntyll the feaſte of Symon and Iude, nexte folowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:79"/>
               <head>¶Henry the .vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nno dom. M.cccc.lxxxv anno primo Henrici ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timi. Hughe Bryce gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmyth knyghte mayre. Iohn Tate, Iohn Swa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxxvi. an ſecondo henrici ſeptimi. Henry Col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>let mercer knyghte mayre, Iohn Perceiuall Hugh Clopton ſhirif.</p>
               <p>This yere the kynge maryed kynge Edwards eldeſt doughter named Elyzabeth,<note place="margin">The king maried.</note> and in Septem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber next after was Prynce Arthur borne at wyncheſter.<note place="margin">Prince Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thar born</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxvii. anno. tercio henrici ſeptimi. Wyllyam Horne mayre, wyllyam Remingto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iohn Fenkell Shiriffes.<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In thys yeare on ſaynct Kathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rins day was the Quene crowned
<pb facs="tcp:26821:80"/> at Weſtminſter.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m, cccc.lxxxviii. anno. iiii. Henrici ſeptimi Roberte Tate Mercer mayre Wylliam Iſaac, Raufe Tylney ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the commons of the North ſlew the Earle of Northum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berland,<note place="margin">Aedmoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</note> in the ſame yeare was the felde of Dykeſmew in Flaunders, foughten by the lorde Dawbeney where the Lorde Morlaye was ſlayne.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxix. anno. v. henrici ſeptimi. Wyllyam Whyte Mayre, Wyllyam Capell, Iohn Broke ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxx. anno .vi. Henrici ſeptimi. Iohn Mathewe Mercer mayre. Henry Coke. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Reuil Hugh Pemperton ſhyr.</p>
               <p>This yere was the Lord Henry
<pb facs="tcp:26821:80"/> the kinges ſeconde ſonne,<note place="margin">The birth of king he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri the .viii</note> borne in Grenewich in Iune.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.cccc.lxxxxi. anno. vii. henrici ſeptimi. Hugh Clapton mercer mayre. Thomas wod wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Browne ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.cccc.lxxxxii. anno viii. henrici ſeptimi. Willyam mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyne ſkynner mayre, william Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate, William welbeke ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere in the moneth of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tobre,<note place="margin">A fray in London.</note> was a fraye made vpon the Eſterlynges by the commons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of London, and ſpeciallye by the mercers ſeruauntes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m, cccc.lxxxxiii. an. ix. henrici ſeptimi. Raufe Auſtrey fiſh monger mayre, Roberte Fabyan, Wyllyam wynger ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare was wheat at ſixe pence the buſhell, and baye ſalte at
<pb facs="tcp:26821:81"/> thre pence. ob. a buſhell in the cyty of London.</p>
               <p>This yeare was ſyr wyllyam Stanley beheaded.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxxxiiii. anno .x. henrici ſeptimi, Rycharde Chawry Salter mayre. Nicholas Alwyn, Iohn warner ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In this yere was good chep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vittell in England</note>This yere was whyte Hearing ſolde for thre ſhyllynges and iiii. pence a barell at London, and not aboue.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.lxxxxv. an. xi. Henrici ſeptimi. Henri Collet mercer knyghte mayre, Thomas kneſworth Henry Somiz Shirif.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxxvi. anno. xii. Henrici ſeptimi. Iohn Tate mercer mayre, Iohn ſhaa, Richard Haddon ſhiriffes,</p>
               <p>This yeare the .xviii. daye of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:81"/> Iune was Blackeheth felde.<note place="margin">Blacke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heth feld.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxxvii. an. xiii Henrici .vii. wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Purchaſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer mayre, Bertylmewe rede Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas wyndone ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.cccc.lxxxxviii. anno xiiii. henrici ſeptimi. Iohn perciual marchaunt tayler mayre, Thomas Braybury, Steuen Ienyns ſhir.</p>
               <p>¶An. do. M.cccc.lxxxxix. an. xv. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rici ſepti. Nicolas alwyne mayre Iames wyford Rychard Broude ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare was the Earle of Warwyke beheaded.<note place="margin">Therle of warwike beheaded</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare the kinge and the Quene ſayled to Callys,<note place="margin">A triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe at Calis.</note> and at Saynte Peters they met with the duke of Burgoyne.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.ccccc. anno. xvi. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici .vii. william Remingto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maire,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:82"/> Iohn Hawes, Wyllyam Siete ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lady ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin landed.</note>This yere the .iiii. day of octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre landed at Plummouth kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin doughter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng of Spaine</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.ccccc.i. anno .xvii. henrici ſeptimi. Iohn ſhaa golde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith mayre, Laurence Aylmer Henry hede ſhiriffes,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prince ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed.</note>This yere vpon. S. Erkinwal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des daye was Prince Arthur ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the foreſayde Lady Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryne, whiche Prynce dyed in the Eaſter weke folowinge.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.ccccc.ii. anno. xviii. Henrici ſeptimi. Bartilmewe Rede goldſmith maire, Henri keb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, Nicolas Niuers Siriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The deth of the quene.</note>This yere the .xi. daie of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary dyed quene Elizabeth in the Towre of London, beyng in child bed and the .viii. daye of Auguſte
<pb facs="tcp:26821:82"/> was the King of Scottes maryed to Margeret the eldeſt doughter.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.ccccc.iii. an. xix. hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rici ſeptimi. Wyllyam Capel dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per mayre, Chryſtopher Hawes, Robert warris Thomas graunge Shiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.ccccc.iiii. an. xx. he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici ſeptimi. Iohn wynger grocer mayre, Roger Achilley Wyllyam browne ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.v. anno. xxi henrici ſeptimi. Thomas Ioyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth fyſhmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger Mayre, Richard Shore, Roger Grouer ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was the wether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke of Poules blowne downe,<note place="margin">The duke of burgon driuen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt.</note> &amp; the duke of Burgoyne was driuen to lande in the weſt Countrey.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.vi. an. xxii.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:83"/> Henriri ſeptimi, Richarde Haddon mercer knyght mayre, wylliam Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynger wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fytzwylliam ſhir.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.cccc.vii. anno. xxiii. Henrici ſeptimi, Wyllyam Browne mercer, Laurence Aymer Mayres, wyllyam Butler, Iohn Kyrby ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A greate fire at nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wytche</note>This yeare was a greate parte of the Cytie of Norwytch brente.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.viii. anno. xxiiii. henrici ſeptimi, Steuen Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nins marchaunte tayler Mayre, Thomas Exmew, Richarde ſmith Shyryffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere the .xxi. daye of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryll, dyed kynge Henry the, vii, at Rychmond the .xxiiii. yeare of hys reygne &amp; is buried at weſtminſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Henry the eyghte.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:83"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt gracious prince Kynge Henry the viii. beganne hys regyne the xxii, day of Apryll in the yeere of oure Lorde .M. ccccc.ix. and was crowned at weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynſter in the Feaſte of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite of ſaynt Iohn Baptyſt nexte folowinge.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini. m.ccccc.ix. anno primo henrici octaui. Thomas Bradbury mercer mayre, George Monox. Iohn Dubet ſhyryffes,</p>
               <p>In this yere was Emſone and Dudley beheaded.<note place="margin">Emſon &amp; dudley be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>headed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thys yere was Syr wyllyam Fytzwyllyam diſfrauncheſed, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wolde not be ſhyrffe.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. m.ccccc.x. an ſecondo henrici octaui, Henri Kebell mayre Iohn mylborne, Iohn Reſt ſhirif.</p>
               <p>This yeare Henry the kynges ſonne was borne at Richmonde,<note place="margin">The birth of king he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries fyrſte ſonne.</note> on
<pb facs="tcp:26821:84"/> newyeres daye: and Iuſtes kepte at weſtminſter, and on ſaynt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes daye the childe died.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. m.ccccc.xi. anno. tercio henrici octaui, Roger Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley draper mayre, Nicolas Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Thomas Myrfyn ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare was the lorde Dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſey ſent into Spayne,<note place="margin">A voyage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſpaine</note> to ayde the kyng of Spayne againſt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but peace was made before hys aryuynge, and ſo he returned home agayne.</p>
               <p>This ſame ſeaſon was ſyr Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Poynynges ſente into Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlande to ayde the Prynce of Chaſtell.<note place="margin">A voyage into gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlande.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame tyme the lorde haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard toke Andrewe berton &amp; a C.lx Scotes, and two fayre Shyppes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno. domini. m.ccccc.xii. anno quarto henrici octaui, wyllyam co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynger
<pb facs="tcp:26821:84"/> Richarde haddon knyghte mayre, Roberte holderne, Roberte Fenrothern Shyryffes.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare was Edward De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lapole beheaded.<note place="margin">Edward delapole beheaded</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thys yeare the lorde Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques dorſet was ſent into Spayne wyth x.M. men,<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſpaine</note> and did much hurt in Guien. and returned in wynter by reaſon of the flyx, and on ſaynct Laurence daye the Regent and the Caricke were brente,<note place="margin">A battale on the ſea</note> whiche were two greate Spyppes.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.xiii. anno. quinto henrici octaui, Wyllyam browne mercer mayre. Iohn Daw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, Iohn Brute ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the ſayde Dawes dyed within the yeare, and in hys place was choſen Roger Baſford.<note place="margin">The lorde Admirall ſlayne.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thys yeare ſyr Edward How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde Lorde Admyrall of England was ſlayne on ſaint Markes daye
<pb facs="tcp:26821:85"/> in Bryttayne by muche hardynes. The ſame yeare in Iune the kinge beſyeged Tyrwyn, and diſcomfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the power of Fraunce, at Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,<note place="margin">Tyrwin &amp; Turney wonne.</note> and toke the cyties Tyrwyn and Turney, and returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more battayle offered du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge whiche tyme the kynge of Scottes enoyed Englande,<note place="margin">The king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſlayne</note> wyth an. C.M. men and was ſlaine him ſelfe, and .xii. Earles by the earle of Surry the kinges lyefe tenaunte wherefore the kynge created hym Duke of Northfolke, and hys el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne Earle of Surrey.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. m.ccccc.xiiii. an. ſexto henrici octaui, Georg monox draper Mayre, Iames yarforde, Ihon Mundy ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A peace concluded betwene England &amp; fraunce</note>This yere was a peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwene England and Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and on ſaynt Denice day the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch kynge maryed the Lady Mary the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:85"/> kynges ſyſter, and on Newyeres day after he dyed, and therefore the kynge ſente for her agayne by the Duke of Suffolke and other.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was Rycharde hunne hanged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lollers Towre<note place="margin">Richarde hun mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers towre</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno do. M.ccccc.xv. anno .vi. henrici octaui. Syr william But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler grocer mayre, henry worle, Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Gray ſhyriffes.</p>
               <p>The ſayde graye died within the yeare and for him was choſen wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bayle.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Februarye, was borne at Grenewitche the Ladye Mary, the Kynges doughter.</p>
               <p>In Aprill the Frenche Quene came into England,<note place="margin">The duke of ſofolke maried the french Quene.</note> and was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the lorde Charles duke of Suffolke.</p>
               <p>This yeare Margaret Quene of Scottes, ſiſter to the kynge fled
<pb facs="tcp:26821:86"/> into England and lay at Harbot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,<note place="margin">The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes fled in to engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> and ſhe was deliuered of a doghter called Margaret, &amp; came to London in may, and taried there a hole yeare, before ſhe returned.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domine. m.ccccc.xvi. anno viii. henrici octaui. Iohn Reſt gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer maire, Thomas Semer, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Thurſtone ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A great froſte.</note>This yere was ſuche a Froſte that al men with cartes might pas betwene weſtminſter &amp; Lambeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">yll Maye daye.</note>This yeare on maye euen, was an inſurreccion of yong perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Alyens of the which diuers were put to execucion, and the reſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due came to weſtminſter wyth hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters aboute their neckes, and were pardoned.</p>
               <p>And the .xxiiii. daye of Maye the quene of Scottes returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſcotlande againe.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.ccccc.xvii. anno .ix.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:86"/> henrici octaui. Syr thomas Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew goldſmith mayre, Thomas baudry Richard Simon ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere was the Terme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourned to Oxford and agayne to London.</p>
               <p>In October the Admyrall of Fraunce came into Englande and Turney was delyuered to the Frenche kynge agayne.<note place="margin">Turney geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. m.ccccc.xviii. an, x. henrici octaui, Thomas Myrfin ſkynner mayre, Iohn Alle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iames Spencer ſhyryffes.<note place="margin">Charles the v. elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yere at Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckford Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the .v. was elected Emperoure.</p>
               <p>This yeare the Earle of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey was ſent into Irelande.<note place="margin">a vſage in to yrelad.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.ccccc.xix. anno. xi henrici octaui, Syr Iames yox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford mercer mayre, Ihon wyllyam Nicholas Pheteryche ſhyryffes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:87"/>
               <p>This yeare the kynge and the Frenche kynge met at the campe betwene Arde and Guynes,<note place="margin">The tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe at Gynes.</note> where were greate triumphes.</p>
               <p>After that the Kynge and the Emperoure mete,<note place="margin">a treu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe at Callis</note> and the kynge wente to Grauelen wyth hym, and he came to Calys wyth the kynge, and had great chere, and the kinge returned.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.ccccc.xx. anno xii. henrici octaui. ſyr Iohn Bruge draper mayre. Iohn Skeuyngton Iohn Keynde ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The duke of buking<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note>This yere the Duke of Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyngham was beheaded the .xxii. daye of maye.</p>
               <p>In Iune the Cardinal went to Calys,<note place="margin">The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Callys</note> to intreate a peace betwene the Emperour &amp; the French kynge and taryed there tyll December with oute anye thynge concluded.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .m.ccccc.xxi. anno
<pb facs="tcp:26821:87"/> xiii. Henrici octa. Syr Iohn Myl borne draper mayre. Iohn Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, Thomas Pargetoure ſhyr.</p>
               <p>This yere the frydaye before Penthecoſt, that is to ſaye the .vi. daye of Iune, Charles the fyfte Emperoure was honorably recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the citie of London of the Mayre, Aldermen,<note place="margin">Thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued into London.</note> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltye, our ſouereigne lorde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying hym. And from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don he wente to winſoure, and ſate in the ſtall of the Garter, and from thence to Hampton, and ſayled o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſea, into Spayne,<note place="margin">a voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> durynge whiche tyme the Earle of Surrey lorde Admirall brente Morles in Bryttayne, and after landed at Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lys, and entred Picardye, &amp; brente townes and caſtels, and beſieged Heſding, but becauſe of wynter he tayſed hys ſeige &amp; returned.<note place="margin">The ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaded Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thys yeare the duke of Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was entringe into Englande
<pb facs="tcp:26821:88"/> wyth a greate armye, but when he harde that the earle of Shrowyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury was commyng to fyght wyth hi, he toke a truce for .vi. moneths.</p>
               <p>¶ An. do. M.ccccc.xxii. an. xiiii. Henrici octaui. Syr Ihon mondy goldſmith mayre, Iohn Rudſtone Ihon Champnies ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The king of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for ſocoure</note>Thys yere Chriſtenrne kynge of Denmarke came into England in Iune.</p>
               <p>This yere the earle of Surrey brente Iedworth,<note place="margin">A voyage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> and many other townes in Scotlande.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wone by the tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note>In this yeare the Turke beſye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged the Roodes, and vpon Chryſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas daye he toke it.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.xxiii. anno. xv. Henrici octaui. Syr Thomas Baudry mercer Mayre, Myghell Englyſhe, Nycolas Ienyns ſhir.</p>
               <p>This yeare the duke of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke
<pb facs="tcp:26821:88"/> was ſente into Fraunce,<note place="margin">A voiage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> with .x.M. menne and paſſed the water of Some without battayle, tooke and deſtroied many townes, and in december he returned.</p>
               <p>The ſame yeare the duke of Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bany beſyeged the caſtel of warke,<note place="margin">The ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes entred england &amp; ſhorly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye.</note> and hearinge of the Earle of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reys commynge with a great army he cowardly fled.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.ccccc.xxiiii. anno. xvi. Henrici octaui. Syr wylliam Bayly draper mayre. Raufe dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer william Roch ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere came from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour the lorde of Champere and other lordes.</p>
               <p>This yere came out of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Biſhop of Dunkell,<note place="margin">Diuers ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors cam i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> &amp; other as Ambaſſadours.</p>
               <p>This yere on ſaynt Mathewes daye was the French kynge taken by the Emperour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:89"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and ſuffolke.</note>This yeare was a metynge in Norfolke and Suffolke for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of money.</p>
               <p>A peace concluded betwene eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and fraunce.</p>
               <p>The frenche kinge was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Marche.<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch king deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of pryſon</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare was the coyne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunced.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. M.ccccc.xxv. anno. xvii. Henrici octaui ſyr Iohn A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyne marcer knyght mayre, Iohn Cau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton, Chriſtopher Aſcue ſhirif.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.ccccc.xxvi. an. xviii. Henrici octaui. Syr Thoms Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer mercer mayre. Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pecoke, Nicholas Lambert ſheryſhes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the corne began to fayle.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinal we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with gret pompe.</note>This yere the Cardinall went into Fraunce with a great pompe where he concluded a peace betwen
<pb facs="tcp:26821:89"/> the kinge and the Frenche kynge, whiche both defied the Emperoure &amp; ſente an army in to Italy and in Septembre he returned.</p>
               <p>In Octobre the greate mayſter of Fraunce came to London,<note place="margin">a leage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; Fraunce.</note> with great triumphe, for concluſion of the ſame leage.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. m.ccccc.xxvii. an. xix. henrici octaui. Syr Iames Spen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer vyntener mayre, Ihon Hardye, wyllyam Holles ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare corne was verye deare,<note place="margin">A dearthe of corne.</note> and had ben dearer if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes of the Stylyard had not bene, and duche ſhippes reſtrayned and an abſtinence of war betwene England and Flaunders.</p>
               <p>On Saynte Denies day a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate came from Rome.<note place="margin">A legate cam from Rome.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Anno domi. m.ccccc.xxviii. an. henrici octaui. Sir Iohn Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
<pb facs="tcp:26821:90"/> draper mayre. Raufe waren, Iohn Longe ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Iune the legates ſat at the blacke freers for the kinges mariage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</note>This yere in Octobre the Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynall was depoſed of the Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler ſhyp.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A peace betwene the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of england &amp; the Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour,</note>This yere was a peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwene the Emperour and the kynge.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. M.ccccc.xxix. an. xxi. Henrici octa. Sir Raufe Dod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer mercer mayre. Myghell Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Walter Champion ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</note>This yeare the Emperour was Crowned at Bonony.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. M.ccccc.xxx. an. xxii. Henrici octaui. Syr Thomas Pargetoure ſalter maire, wyllyam dauney, Iohn Clopynge ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere was the French kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:26821:90"/> Children delyuered.</p>
               <p>One boyled in ſmithfelde for poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonynge.</p>
               <p>This yeare dyed the Cardynalle on ſaynt Andrewes euen.<note place="margin">The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal died</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini .m.ccccc.xxxi. an. xxiii. henrici octaui Nicholas La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert grocer mayre. Richard Greſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Edward Attam ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the kyng began to buylde his place at weſtminſter.<note place="margin">the pales at weſtmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter bilded</note>
               </p>
               <p>In this yeare was Griffeth Ryſe beheaded.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Octobre the king went ouer the ſea and met with the Frenche kynge.</p>
               <p>¶Anno do. m.ccccc.xxxii. an. xxiiii henrici octaui. Sir ſteuen Pecoke haberdaſher mayre. Richard Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolde. Richarde Pinthon, Ihon martyne ſhiriffe.</p>
               <p>This yerae the kinge was
<pb facs="tcp:26821:91"/> by due proces of the law diuorſed from lady Katherine his brothers wife,<note place="margin">The king deuorſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers wif</note> and he maryed Lady Anne Boleine,<note place="margin">The king maried.</note> which was crowned Que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne on whitſonday.</p>
               <p>On midſomer daye died the french quene, wife vnto the Duke of Suffolke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lady eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth borne.</note>This yere was borne the ladye Elizabeth at Grenewetch, on the euen of the Natiuitie of our Lady</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.xxxiii. an. xxv. Henri octaui. Chriſtopher Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue knyght draper mayre Wylly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Forman, Thomas Kitſon Shiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The holy maid of kent &amp; her compani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons put to death,</note>This yeare was a Nunne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the holy mayde of Kente, two monkes, and two frees and a preeſt hanged and headed for treaſon, blaſphemy, and ypocreſye.</p>
               <p>This yeare was a peace conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded with Scotlande.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:91"/>
               <p>This yere was the Biſhop of Rome with all his falſe vſurped power abboliſhed quite out of the Realme.<note place="margin">The by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. m.ccccc.xxxiiii. an, xxvi. Henrici octaui. Syr Iohn Chamnies ſkynner mayre, Nycho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Leueſon Wyllyam Denham Shiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere the earle of Kildare dyed in the Towre,<note place="margin">The erle of kildare rebeled.</note> and hys ſonne rebelled and ſlewe the Byſhop of Deuilynge, wherefore the kynge ſente ſyr Wyllyam Skeuyngton theyther.<note place="margin">The fyrſt frute of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtye grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the kynge.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thys yeare was graunted to the Kyng the fyrſte frutes and the tenthes of all ſpiritual poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>In Iune was the byſhoppe of Rocheſter, and ſyr Thomas more,<note place="margin">The byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſter &amp; ſyr tomas more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> beheaded for denyinge the kynge to be ſupreme heade of the Church of Englande.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:92"/>
               <p>And in this yere were thre mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the Charterhouſe executed for the ſame offence.<note place="margin">Thre mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter houſe put to deathe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Anno do. M.ccccc.xxxv. anno. xxvii. Henrici octa. Syr Iohn Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyn mercer the ſecond tyme mayre, Humfrey Mommoth, Iohn Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere was Quene Anne, the lorde Rocheforde,<note place="margin">Quene an beheaded.</note> Nores, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, Brereton, and Markes behea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. And the kynge maryed Lady Iane Semer.</p>
               <p>This yere in Octobre begane a folyſhe commocion in Lincolne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colneſhere</note> and in yorkeſhire, by meanes of the Lorde Dercie, the Lord Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. ſyr Robert Conſtably, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Aſke, whiche by the kynges wyſedome and his prudente coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell were appeaſed wythout bloude ſhedynge.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. m.ccccc.xxxvi. anno
<pb facs="tcp:26821:92"/> xxviii. Henrici octaui, ſyr Raufe Warren mercer Mayre, Rycharde Paget, Wyllyam Boyer ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the kynge and the Quene rode thorow London, with a goodly company.</p>
               <p>In February was Thomas Fetzgaret and fyue of hys vncles hanged drawen and quartered.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare the Lorde Derſey, ſyr Fraunces Bygot, ſyr Roberte Conſtable, and other began a new conſpyracy,<note place="margin">A new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mocion.</note> whych were attaynted and put to death in Iune.</p>
               <p>This yere on ſaynt Edwardes euen,<note place="margin">The birth of king ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the vi. ano. 1537</note> was Prynce Edward borne at Hampton Courte.</p>
               <p>This yeare the .xxiii. day of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tobre, died Quene Iane, and is bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed at wynſore.</p>
               <p>¶Anno. dom, M.ccccc.xxxvii. an xxix. henrici octaui. Rychard Greſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham mayre. Iohn Greſham, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb facs="tcp:26821:93"/> Lewyn ſhyriffes.</p>
               <p>Thys yete begane the colletion for the poore, and a greate nombre were cured of manye greuous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, thorowe the Charity therof.</p>
               <p>In Maye was frier Foreſt han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">Frier fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> and brente in ſmithfelde for treaſon and hereſy.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. M.ccccc.xxxviii. an xxx. Henrici octaui. Syr Wyllyam Forman mayre, Wyllyam wylkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Nicholas Gibſon ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ques of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etor behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>This yeare in Decembre was the Marques of Exceter, the lorde Montacute and ſyr Edwarde Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, beheaded for hygh treaſon due<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly proued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A noble muſter in London.</note>In May, the Cytezyns of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don muſtred all in bryghte harnes and cotes of white ſylke, wyth whit cloth, and chaynes of golde, in thre greate battaylles, to the great wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſtraungers.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:93"/>
               <p>¶Anno dom. M.ccccc.xxxix. anno xxxi. Henrici octaui, ſyr wyllyam Holleys mayre, Iohn Fayre, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Huntlowe ſheriffe.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Nouembre,<note place="margin">4. abbot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s put to death for treaſon</note> the Abbot of Redynge Glaſtenbury, &amp; Colcheſter, were attaynted of hygh treaſon, and lyke traytours put to deathe.</p>
               <p>The .xxviii. daye of Iuly,<note place="margin">Thomas cromwell beheaded</note> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Crumwell, late before created Earle of Eſſex, and water Lorde Hungerford were beheaded at the Towre hyll for treaſon.</p>
               <p>And the .xxx. daye were Barnes, Garet, and Hierom brent for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye. Alſo the ſame daye were Abell Powell, and Fetherſtone, drawen, hanged, and quartered, in Smyth felde for treaſon.</p>
               <p>This Somer was a great heat and droughte, ſo that in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the people woulde haue gyuen one buſhell, for the grendyng of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:94"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An exami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion of byſhopes.</note>Thys yeare was the Byſhop of Chycheſter, and Doctor wylſon, delyuered oute of the towre vpon the kynges pardon.</p>
               <p>¶Anno. dom. m.ccccc.xl. an, xxxxii Henrici octaui, ſyr Wyllyam Roch mayre, Wylliam Laxton, ſyr Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyn Bowes ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">great pity</note>Thys yeare the collection for the poore people ſeaſed.</p>
               <p>In Decembre were Egerton &amp; Harman put to execucion for coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfetyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges great Seale</p>
               <p>This yere the kinges grace bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great buildi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at Calis &amp; Guynes.</p>
               <p>In Apryl, certaine preeſtes and laye men began a new commocion in yorkeſhyre,<note place="margin">A new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocion in yorkeſhire</note> whiche were ſhortly taken and put to death in dyuerſe places, one Leghte, and two other were put to deathe at London, the xxvii. daye of Maye, and for that
<pb facs="tcp:26821:94"/> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was ſyr Iohn Neuel knight draune, hanged, and quartered,<note place="margin">Due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion.</note> at yorke on corpus Chriſti euen, and xxx. handged for robbery.</p>
               <p>This yeare the .vi. day of May, there was a proclamacion that the Byble ſhould be had in euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſh Churche, within this realme,<note place="margin">Goddes word ſet at lyberty</note> redye for all ſortes of people, to reade and heare Goddes worde at conuenient tymes.</p>
               <p>This yere the counteſſe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſburye was beheaded the .xxviii. day of maye.</p>
               <p>The .ix. daye of Iune, were two yeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kinges Garde,<note place="margin">Right iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement.</note> hanged at Grenewitch for robberye in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of al other.</p>
               <p>And the .x. day of Iune, was ſir Edmond Kneuet knighte arayned in the Kynges Hall there for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge a blow in the kinges houſe, and ſhoulde haue loſte his hand, if the kinges maieſtie had not exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:26821:95"/> hys mercy towardes him.</p>
               <p>The .xxii. daye of Iulye, there was another proclamacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Abrogaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye dayes.</note> that no holy day ſhoulde be kepte (excepte) our ladies dayes, the Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelyſtes, S. George, S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalene. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> S. Marke ſhal not be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne kept as a faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g day, nor S. Laurence euen. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Chyldren ſhoulde be der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ne go aboute vpon ſaynt Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, ſaynt Katheryne ſaynt Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the holy Innocentes, &amp; ſuche lyke dayes.</p>
               <p>Alſo the .xxviii. daye of Iuly, was the lord Leonard Grey behea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded at Towre hill for diuers trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons done in Irela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d while he was the kinges deputy there.</p>
               <p>The ſame daye were thre Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilmen, called Mantell, Roydon, &amp; Frowes, hanged at ſayncte Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas waterynges, for comminge a ſhameful murther, and making an
<pb facs="tcp:26821:95"/> vnlawfull aſſemble confirmed by a ſedicious oth in Suſſex,<note place="margin">A vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble</note> in May laſte, in the companye of the Lorde Dacres of the South, which lorde Dacres was on ſ. Peters daye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing led fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Towre through London, by the Sheryffes on fote to Tyborne, and there hanged.</p>
               <p>And the firſt daye of Iuly, was a Welchman drawen, hanged, and quartered for propheſyinge of the noble kinge Henrye the eyghtes deathe.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini. M.ccccc.xli. an. xxxiiii. henrici octaui. Syr Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Dormer mayre, Syr Rouland Hyl, Henry Suckley ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare, the .x. daye of Marche there was a maide boyled in Smithfelde for poyſonynge of diuers honeſt perſons that ſhe had dwelled wyth, in the Citie of londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare, came in the Earle
<pb facs="tcp:26821:96"/> of Deſmonde and the great Oneil oute of Irelande, and did ſubmyt theim to the kinges maieſtie,<note place="margin">yryſh men called to honoure</note> and after their ſubmiſſion, the great O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyll was created Earle of Tyron &amp; his ſonne Baron of Doncannen.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domini. M.ccccc.xlii. an. xxxiiii. Henrici octaui. Iohn Cotes ſalter mayre Henry Hobelthorne, Henry Amcotes ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lacke of wood in London</note>In this yeare the Froſt dured ſo longe that many of the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cried out for lacke of wode and coles, that the mayre wente to the wood wharfes, and ſold to the pore people Byllet and Fagot, by the peny worth.</p>
               <p>And this yeare was an Acte of parliamente,<note place="margin">An act for wod &amp; cole in london</note> for woode and cole to kepe the full ſyſe, after the purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lady, that ſhuld be in the yere of our lorde. M.ccccc.xliii that no manne ſhuld bargayne, ſel,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:96"/> bringe or conuaye to be vttered or ſolde, vpon payne of forfiture.</p>
               <p>This yeare the .xxviii. daye of Iulye, was brente at winſore three perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, one ſir Anthony parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Preeſt and two ſeculer men, &amp; the thyrd had the kinges pardon</p>
               <p>Alſo this yere was proclamed in the Citie of London the thirde day of Auguſt,<note place="margin">Ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> war towarde fraunce.</note> open war betwene our ſoueraigne Lorde the kynge &amp; the Frenche kinge, ſo the kynges hyghnes geuinge licence and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thororitie to euery of his ſubiectes to vſe the ſayde Frenche kinge and al that depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon him, to their moſte aduauntage and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as his maieſties enemies hath in ſuche lyke caſe heretofore bene vſed and accuſtomed.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domi. M.ccccc.xliiii. an. xxxv. Henrici octaui. Syr Wylly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Bower draper, whiche deceaſed
<pb facs="tcp:26821:97"/> being mayre, &amp; after him was choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyr Raufe warren. Iohn Rowles, Richard Dobbes ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere was a greate deathe in London,<note place="margin">A greate deathe.</note> whiche continued ſo longe, that ther was no terme kept at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Mighelmas, but was remoued to ſaynt Albones, &amp; there kepte.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A voiage into ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</note>In the yere of our lord. M.ccccc xliii. and the .xxxvi. yere of our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raygne lorde kinge Henry the .viii in the time of the mairaltie of ſyr Rafe Waren, the kinges maieſtie ſente an army into Scotlande the iiii. day of May, and landed at lith and ſo wente burning and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge the countrey about, ſparinge neyther Caſtell, towne, Pyle, ne Village.</p>
               <p>The boroughe and towne of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborough, with the Abbey called Holy Rode houſe, and the kinges Palice adioyned to the ſame, were
<pb facs="tcp:26821:97"/> dyſtroyed. The towne of Lyth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and the hauen and peyre deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. The caſtell &amp; village of Crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myller, the Abbey of Newbottell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and parte of Muſkel borow towne the Chapell of oure lady of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, Preeſton towne and the caſtell Harintwone with the Freers and nunnery, a caſtel of Oliuer Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, the towne of Dunbar, Laure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone with the Graunge.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>¶Drilaw.</item>
                  <item>Weſter crag.</item>
                  <item>Enderlaugh</item>
                  <item>The pyle &amp; the towne.</item>
                  <item>Broughton.</item>
                  <item>Cheſter felles.</item>
                  <item>Crawned.</item>
                  <item>Dudiſtone.</item>
                  <item>Stanhouſe.</item>
                  <item>The Fycket,</item>
                  <item>Beuerton.</item>
                  <item>Tranent</item>
                  <item>Shenſtoue.</item>
                  <item>Markle.</item>
                  <item>Tarpren.</item>
                  <item>Kyrlande hyll.</item>
                  <item>Katherwike,</item>
                  <item>Belton.</item>
                  <item>Eaſt Barnes.</item>
                  <item>Howlande.</item>
                  <item>Buterden.</item>
                  <item>Quicwod.</item>
                  <item>Blacburne.</item>
                  <item>Raunton.</item>
                  <item>Byldy &amp; the towre.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:98"/>
               <p>And manye other townes and villages brente by the fleete vpon the ſea ſyde,<note place="margin">A rode in to ſcotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</note> with a greate nombre of pyles and vilages which I can not name nor reherſe, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and left deſolate, Kyncorne S. Myners, the quenes Fery, part of Peting waies: and other diuers thinges done by the Earle of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford lyuetenant to the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye.</p>
               <p>At Lythe in Scotlande were made fyue and forty knightes.</p>
               <p>Alſo this yere, the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty prepared an army into frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and thither he wente his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone,<note place="margin">Buleine &amp; mutrel be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeged.</note> beſeiged the ſtronge towne of Bullen in Pycardy, as here after ye ſhall here.</p>
               <p>The .xiiii. day of Iuly the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtye departed from douer to Callys.</p>
               <p>The .xv. daye of Iuly, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye remoued to Morgyſen, and
<pb facs="tcp:26821:98"/> there camped one night.</p>
               <p>The, xxvi. day of Iuly, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty remoued to hie Bulleine, and there camped on the Northeſt part of the towne.</p>
               <p>The .xxvii. daye of Iulye my Lord of Suffolke layde ſyege vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hyghe Bulleyn, and there cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on the Eaſte parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne.</p>
               <p>The .xxviii. daye of Iulye, the watche towre otherwyſe called, the Olde man was wonne.</p>
               <p>The .xxix. daye of Iulye, Baſe-Bullen was wonne.</p>
               <p>The .xi. day of September was made a greate Larum, and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell was ſo ſhaken with gunpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, that the ſtones whiche wayed xxx. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wayght, dyd flye twenty ſcore of, the which not lytell greued the inhabitours to theyr daily pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and tormentes.</p>
               <p>The .xiii. daye of Septembre the towne was victoryouſlye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb facs="tcp:26821:99"/> by the mooſte dreade ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne Lord kinge Henry the eight, kinge of Englande Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the faith, and in earthe ſupreme head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Englande and Irelande,<note place="margin">Bolleyne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered.</note> which after the entreaty and humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion made of the French men, gaue them licence to take bag and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage with them and ſo departe.</p>
               <p>The .xiiii. daye of Septembre, at iii. of the cloke at after none, the towne gate was opened, and the people began to come out, and they helde on vntyll .vii. of the clocke at nyghte. And there were in nomber of men wemen and chyldren .iiii. M. and of them .xv.C. able men of warre,<note place="margin">The kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence.</note> and they had with theim as muche as they could cary both me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, women, and children, that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare any thynge, and theyr horſes and kyne were loded with as much ſtuffe as they could beare
<pb facs="tcp:26821:99"/> away. And they had .lxxv, wagens laded with them, what laude and prayſe oughte they to geue vnto God, what worthye ſalutacions ought they to render to ſuch a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and valiaunte Prynce. O howe ought they to pray dayly for the proſperous reigne of this victo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious and puyſſaunt Prince which ſhewed them ſuche mercye and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, with ſafegarde of their lifes.</p>
               <p>The .xv. day of September the kinges maieſtie entred into hyghe Bullen with the nobilitie of hys realme, and trumpettes blowinge,<note place="margin">The king entred bulle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure.</note> that it reioyſed all the whole hoſte to heare, and woulde haue comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all true Engliſhe mens hartes to haue hard, and ſene the victorye and conqueſt that was had by our mooſte dread ſoueraygne ouer the mayden towne, for the whiche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, prayſe and glorye be gyuen to almighty God, grace and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:26821:100"/> frome god the father, vnto the Kynge for euer. Amen.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. M.ccccc.xliiii. an. xxxvi. Henrici octaui. Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton mayre, Iohn wylford, Andrew Iud ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>The fyrſte day of Octobre, the kinges grace departed from Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len toward Douer. And at his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge he dubbed fowre knightes at the waters ſyde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A brag of the french meane.</note>The .viii. daye of Octobre, the Dolphin came with a great power out of highe Fraunce and camped at Morgyſen and ſent his trompet with .ii.C. horſemen and men of ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes towarde Bulle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on the Northeaſte ſyde where the kinges grace camped, and the trumpetter came to Bullen gate, &amp; blewe his trumpet to come to my Lorde Deputie, and taried at the gate from .ix. of the clocke before
<pb facs="tcp:26821:100"/> noone, tyll .ii. of the clocke at after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and then he came into Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len to my Lorde deputye and ſayd the Dolphyn hys maſter had ſente to ſomon the towne. And my Lord deputie and the Counſell gaue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the Dolphin of defiaunce, and then the trumpet and the buſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of horſmen marched backe to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward Morgyſen.</p>
               <p>Shortly after, beſyde diuerſe and many ſharpe ſkimiſhes,<note place="margin">A ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh at Bolleyne.</note> made by the Frenchemen at Bullen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by the Dolphyn with a great power whiche in the night ſeaſon, ſtale vpon Baſe Bullein, takynge there a greate ſorte of ſycke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, and women in their beddes whome withoute mercy they ſlewe. Howbe it ſo manfully the Englyſh men, whyche eſcaped oute of Baſe Bullein, behaued them ſelfes, get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge weapons oute of the highe towne, that they bet the Frenche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:26821:101"/> agayne out of the Baſe towne and after with helpe of the hyghe towne, they ſlewe a greate nomber of them, and ſo agayne poſſeſſed quietly, the ſayde Baſe towne. And the .x. day of Octobre the Dolphin ſent his trumpetter to the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie of Bullein to knowe what capitaines, men of Armes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his men the Englyſhe men had taken. The Lorde Deputye made anſwer and ſayde he had but one. Then the Dolphins trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſayde, that they lacked of theyr captaines men of armes and other of theyr fote men to the nombre of vii.C. and mo. And the Lorde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie deliuered the french captaine and the Dolphin deliuered oures.</p>
               <p>The .xi. day of Octobre came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great nauy of French ſhyps right before Bullein, and they remained in ſighe two dayes, and then ſayled forth betwene Bullein and Calis,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:101"/> to heare of their maſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dolphin</p>
               <p>This yeare was taken by the kinges ſhyppes of the Weſt coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey and of the Engliſh coſtes, the nombre of .ccc. Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch ſhips &amp; more.</p>
               <p>The .xxvi. day of Ianuary in the yeare of .xlv. there camped on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſte ſyde of Bullen beyonde the haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an army of frenchmen to the nombre of .xviii. M. and lay there the ſpace of .x. dayes. And the .vi. day of February they were all put to flight by the Erle of Harford &amp; the lord Admyral, then beyng lord Deputie of Bullen with a ſmal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany of men, &amp; without any blud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheding on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh ſide, but dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of them were ſlaine. And they left al their ordinaunce with bag &amp; baggage behind them, after which victory Sir Thomas Poyninges was made Lord.</p>
               <p>This yeare in Iuly about the xx. day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frenchmen wyth a greate
<pb facs="tcp:26821:102"/> Nauy of ſhyppes enuaded the Ile of Wyghte,<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men enua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the ile of wight.</note> where as they wer dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen backe and a greate nombre ſlayne.</p>
               <p>This yerae in Septembre the Church of Saynt Gyles withoute Cripilgate was brent.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini. M.ccccc.xlv. an. xxxvii. Henrici octa. Syr Martyn Bowes goldſmith mayre, George Barnes, Raufe Aleine ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>This yere in February ſholde a woman bene brente in Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fmithfelde for clyppyng of Golde, but the kinges pardonne came ſhe beynge at the ſtake readye to bee brente.</p>
               <p>Thys yere the Cytizyns of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don leuaied in the cyty, ii. fyfienes for the conueyaunce of more wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the citie.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare the .xiii. day of Iune beynge whytſonday, and the yeare
<pb facs="tcp:26821:102"/> of our lorde God. M.ccccc.xlvi. a continuall peace was proclaymed in the citie of London betwene our moſt renomed Henry the eyghte on the one partye.<note place="margin">A peace be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twen eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land and Fraunce,</note> And the ryght hygh and myghtye prynce the Frenche kynge on the other partye, with a ſolempne proceſſion at the tyme of proclamacion gyuynge laude and praiſe to god the auctour of peace, and at nyght thorowoute the Citie greate fyers with muche ioye and gladnes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the .xxvii. daye of Iune docter Crome preached at Poules croſſe,<note place="margin">Docter crome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted.</note> and there openly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed that he had ben ſeduced with noughtye Bokes, contrarye to the true doctrine of Chriſt, and in this doyng he ſayd he was not compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo for to ſaye, neyther for feare nor by any other meanes, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of his free and voluntary wyll.</p>
               <p>This yere was brent in ſmith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felde,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:103"/> Anne Aſcue, and thre more for heriſy, and Doctor ſhaxſton re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted the ſame time.</p>
               <p>In the ſame yeare the .xxi. day of Auguſte,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the year.</note> came into englande to do his duety from the french kinge Mounſcure Deneball high admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of Fraunce wyth greate try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe, and broughte with him the Sacre of Depe &amp; .xii. Galeis well beſene in diuers poyntes and ſo landed at the Towre, where as he was honorablye receyued with ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie nobles and peres of the realme and with the greateſt ſhotinge of Gunnes that euer was hearde or ſene, and ſo broughte to the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Londons place and lay there ii. nyghtes, that is to ſaye the xxi. &amp; .xxii. day of Auguſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yere of oure lorde. M.ccccc.xlvi.</p>
               <p>On the monday the .xxiii. day of Auguſt, he dyd ryd to Hampton courte, where as the kinges grace
<pb facs="tcp:26821:103"/> lay, and before he came to Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Court, my Lorde the prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued him with the nobleſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that euer was ſene, to the nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of .cccc.xl. veluet cotes. And my lord Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces leuery wer with ſleues of cloth of golde, and halfe the cote imbrodred alſo with golde, there were to the nombre of .viii.c. horſes ryally apparelled, which broughte him to the Maner of Hampton Courte to the prudent and redub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prynce his father, and Quene Katheryne, and on the morowe, the kynges grace and the ſaid Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Deueball brake the hooſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them, for a generall peace, &amp; ſo continued in banketynge and pleaſure triumphantlye wyth the nobleſt Maſkes and mumminges that euer was ſene, with diuers &amp; ſundry chaunges in ſo muche that the torche berers were clothed in cloth of golde, this continued .vi.
<pb facs="tcp:26821:104"/> daies and ſo returned into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with manye ſundrye gyftes gyuen him and his retynew.</p>
               <p>¶An. do. m.ccccc.xlvi. an. xxxviii herici. viii Henri Hobelthorne mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunte Tayloure mayre, Richard Gerues, Thomas Curtes ſhiriffes</p>
               <p>This yeare the .xix. day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, was the Erle of Surrey be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>headed at the Towre hyl for treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare the .xxviii. daye of Ianuary departed this preſent life the noble king Henry the eyght of that name, whoſe ſoule God take to his infinite mercy vnder whome we his people of Englande lyued longe a ioyful and a peaſable lyfe,<note place="margin">The deth of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the .viii</note> reduced from the errour of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to the true knowledge of God and his worde. And was full roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally buryed at Wynfore, the .xvi. day of February the ſame yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:104"/>
               <head>¶Edwarde the .vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vre moſt gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne lorde kyng Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the .vi. beganne his raygne the .xxxi. daye of Ianuary in the yere of our lord .m.ccccc.xlvi, and was proclaimed ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in all his late fathers realmes and landes. And the .xix. day of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, he rode ſolemply with his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ſyr Edward Seymer, Lord go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, and Protectour, Duke of Somerſet, with the nobilitie of the realme from the towre to Weſtmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thorowe the citie of London, whiche was richelye hanged with couerlites, and carpettes of tapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and ares, Chepeſyde being ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chely hanged with clothe of ſiluer and golde. Euery condite running wine, Pagentes of chyldren beyng rychely aparelled to receiue him at euerye place with Oracons of his
<pb facs="tcp:26821:105"/> prayſe. And on the Southe ſyde of ſaynt Poules churcheyard an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſie came from the battilment of the ſame churche, vpon a cable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge made faſte to an anker at the deanes doore, lying vpon his breſt aidinge him ſelfe nether with hand nor fote, and after, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the mid of the ſame cable, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many pretye toyes, where at the kynge with other of the peres and nobles of thys Realme laughed hertelye.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde</note>The .xx. daye of February hys moſte noble grace at Weſtminſter was proclaymed, anoynted, &amp; crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned kynge. Thomas lord Archebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Cantorbury and Metera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polytane of this Realme, miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the deuine Sacramentes, &amp; ceremonies to do ryallye al thynge belonginge, and ſo continued in banketynge triumphantlye wyth the nobleſt maſkes and mumme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:26821:105"/> that euer was ſene, wyth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundry chaunges of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell.</p>
               <p>The, xxi. and .xxii. day, ſyr Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Seymer lorde Admyrall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Deuelox, ſyr An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony kingſtone, ſyr Peter Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, Knowles, and Shelley, were Chalengers agaynſt al perſonnes defendaunte at the Tylte, bariers and turney, wherein they behaued themſelues lyke valiaunte men of armes. And this was finiſhed on Sonday nexte folowinge, beynge the .xxvii. day hauinge at euen ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kettes, at the which were ſuche dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundry playes with maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that no tyme tongue, nor pen can expreſſe.</p>
               <p>In this moneth of March, ſyr Andrewe Dudley viſe Admirall with the Paunce and the Hart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge but ſynglye manned, had a great conflycte with thre Scottiſh
<pb facs="tcp:26821:106"/> ſhippes beynge double manned, and tri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med with ordinaunce in the narowe Seas, and thankes be to God obteyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory, and toke many priſoners, and broughte the ſhyppes into Orwell hauen, where they dyd remaine. For the whiche victory, let vs praiſe God, praying God for the proſperous raygne &amp; longe life of oure Lord and kynge Edward the ſixte, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory ouer his enemyes, and for the welthe of this Realme.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domi. M.ccccc.xlvii. an. primo Edwardi ſexti. Syr Iohn Greſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knighte Mayre, Thomas White Robert Curtes ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yere was ordeyned the holye Communion to be receyued in both kindes.</p>
               <p>This yere the laſt day of Iuly Stephen Gardener byſhoppe of Wincheſter was commaunded to
<pb facs="tcp:26821:106"/> the tower of london.</p>
               <p>Tis yeare was a great morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in London, then was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement geuen to al Curates that they ſhoulde burye none a fore ſix of the cloke in the morning nor after ſixe at night, and that the bell ſhoulde ringe three quarters of an houre or more.</p>
               <p>¶ Anno domi. m.ccccc.xlviii. an. ſeconde Edwardi ſexti. Henri Amp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cotes fiſhmonger Mayre, wylliam Locke, Iohn Aylufe ſheriffes.</p>
               <p>In this yeare was images put downe in all churches thorowe Englande.<note place="margin">Idolatry forbedden</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yere the mariage of pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes was graunted lawfullye by the lawes of God.<note place="margin">Laufull for preſtes to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare doctoure Bonnar was depoſed of his biſhoppricke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of October.</p>
               <p>In this moueth the Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:26821:107"/> Somerfet was committed to the Towre.</p>
               <p>¶Anno domini .M.ccccc.xlix. an. tercio Edwardi ſexti. Syr Roland Hyl knight Mayre. Robert yorke, Iohn Turke ſhiriffes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſhyre.</note>This yeare was a ryſynge in Deuenſhire and Cornewale about the myddes of the yere: which was domage to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other: wherfore their chiefe captanies were taken and broughte to the tower of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: and the .xxvi. day of Ianuary after was drawen, hanged, and quartered, &amp; thre more at tydurne.</p>
               <p>Alſo this yeare about the ſame time was an Inſurreccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Norf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and Suffolke.<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on in nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>folke.</note> And theyr chefe Captaine captaine Kyte and his brothere were ſhortlye after ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and Iudged to bee hanged at Norwiche in chaynes.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the yeare of oure Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:26821:107"/> God. M.ccccc.l. the .xix. day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary captayne Ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>balde: the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpainieardes, &amp; an other captaine was ſlaine without New gate in an euenyng by a Fleming: whiche was taken and hanged on the euen of S. Paule, and iii. more with him in Smithfelde.</p>
               <p>The .vi. day of February came the Duke of Somerſet oute of the Towre.</p>
               <p>In the ſame moneth went oute of Englande certayne Lordes of the counſayle to Bulleyne,<note place="margin">A peace co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded.</note> where certayne of the French counſel met with them, and after longe conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion had, and diuers metynges betwene them, there was a general peace concluded, which peace was proclaymed the .xxix. day of march folowinge.</p>
               <p>Alſo about the .xxv. day of Aprill folowinge,<note place="margin">Bulle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> the towne of Bulleine with the Fortreſſes therunto belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging,
<pb facs="tcp:26821:108"/> was deliuered by the engliſh men, into the handes of the French menne.</p>
               <p>In this yere the ſecond day of Maye was a woman brente in Smithfeld callled Ioane Kenll o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called Ioane Bocher for the horrible heriſie,<note place="margin">one brent for hereſy</note> that Chriſt toke no fleſhe of the vyrgyn Mary, and at her deathe dyd preache Mayſter Iohn Scory a preacher of Cantor bury, ſhewinge vnto the people her abhomynable opinions, warnyng al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beware of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſuch lyke.</p>
               <p>About this tyme ther were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine lighte perſonnes pretended a new commocion in Kente, but they were apprehended, and on the .xiii. day of Maye was for that treſpas hanged at Aſheford Richard Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Goddard Goram and the next day folowing was hanged at Can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torbury Richard Irelande for the ſame treſpace.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26821:108"/>
               <p>¶Anno dom, M.ccccc.l. anno, iiii Edwardi ſexti. Syr Andrew Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner knight mayre, Auſten hinde, Iohn Lyon ſhyryffes.</p>
               <p>The .xxv. day of Maye was an erthquake in Sothery and in part of Medelſex.<note place="margin">An earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This yeare on. S. Valentines daye at feuerſham in Kent was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted a ſhamefull mourther for one Arden a gentilman was by the conſente of hys wyfe mourthered wherfore ſhe was brent at Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,<note place="margin">A ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>full murther.</note> and there was one hanged in Chaynes for that mourther, and at Feuerſham was .ii. hanged in chay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and a woman brente, and in ſmithfelde was hanged one Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by and his ſyſter for the ſame mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo.</p>
               <p>This yeare was Steuen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dener Biſhop of Wyncheſter cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to iuſtice at La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>beth before the kynges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſioners and the .xvi.<note place="margin">Steuen gardener depoſed.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26821:109"/> daye of February for his manyfeſt contempte and continuall diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or rather rebellion againſt the kynges maieſty, wherof he was iuſtly depreued of his eſtate of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thys yeare was a duche man brent in Smithfelde for holdynge of the opinion of the Auryans.</p>
               <p>¶Anno dom. M.ccccc.li. anno. v Edwardi ſexti. Richarde Dobbes ſkinner mayre, Iohn La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bert Iohn Coper ſhiryffes.</p>
               <p>This yeare the ſeconde daye of Nouember the old quene of Scot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes came to london which was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably receiued and lodged in the Biſhops palace.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A hie flod</note>In this yeare the .xiii. daye of Ianuary the ſea brake in at ſand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witche inſomuche that it did ouer flowe al the Marſhes thereaboute and drowned muche cattell to the
<pb facs="tcp:26821:109"/> greate loſſe bothe of the towne and countre.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>Here I ſhoulde haue put in the notable waies from certaine cities to Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſome of them be not marked truely wherefore I left them out till ſuch tyme as I haue more knowlege in theſe waies</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Cantorbu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry in ſaynt Paules pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe by Iohn Mychell.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
